<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Earl of Castlemain's manifesto</title>
            <title>Manifesto</title>
            <author>Castlemaine, Roger Palmer, Earl of, 1634-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8304</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13104671</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13104671</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97478</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31233)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97478)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 410:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Earl of Castlemain's manifesto</title>
                  <title>Manifesto</title>
                  <author>Castlemaine, Roger Palmer, Earl of, 1634-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 136 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An account of Castlemaine's arrest and trial for high treason during the period of the Popish Plot.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Page 2 is taped; p. 20 is torn; p. 43-44 are tightly bound, and p. 92 is misnumbered in filmed copy. Beginning-p. 55 photographed from Cambridge University Library copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Castlemaine, Roger Palmer, --  Earl of, 1634-1705.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:97478:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97478:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97478:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi>: Roger Earle of Castlemayne Baron of Limbrick. etc.</head>
                  <figDesc>Engraved portrait (head and shoulders) of the 1st Earl of Castlemaine (1634-1705), in a laurel wreath frame.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97478:2"/>
            <p>THE EARL OF CASTLEMAIN's Manifeſto.</p>
            <q>Nec poteſt aut Veritas cum vi, aut Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia cum credulitate conjungi.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Lact.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed Anno 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="manifesto">
            <pb facs="tcp:97478:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97478:3"/>
            <head>THE EARL of <hi>CASTLEMAIN'S</hi> MANIFESTO.</head>
            <p>HAving had the misfortune to be accus'd, (if he can call it ſo, that has been openly acquitted and freed,) I left the <hi>Publication</hi> of all Particulars, to thoſe who ſtill furniſh'd the Curious with Tranſactions of that nature; But ſeeing they have been not a little faulty in my <hi>Tryal,</hi> which yet came not out till the end of laſt <hi>January</hi> 5 and ſeeing Mr. <hi>Turbervile</hi> has been as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant as any of his fellows, in his wild printed <hi>Charge</hi> againſt me, I think it now an incumbent <hi>Duty</hi> to give the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97478:4"/>World, (and conſequently Poſterity) a full Account of my <hi>Troubles,</hi> ſince theſe unparallel'd <hi>Diſorders,</hi> which have not only diſturb'd the flouriſhing State of <hi>England,</hi> but aſtoniſh'd and amaz'd the whole Univerſe alſo.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament</hi> (according to the time appointed at their <hi>July Prorogation</hi>) meeting again on <hi>Munday</hi> the 21ſt. of <hi>October</hi> 1678. Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> was order'd (on the 2d. day following) by the <hi>Lower Houſe,</hi> to acquaint them with the <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars</hi> of the <hi>Plot,</hi> which he did in a Diſcourſe of many hours, being for the moſt part the ſame, as that in the <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative,</hi> ſince printed by his leave and directions. But the thing expected with the greateſt Impatience by the whole <hi>Town,</hi> was an account of the <hi>Perſons</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated to the <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> Imployments mention'd by him; and this he was to give in (as he did) the next day; whereupon the <hi>Houſe</hi> ſent for the <hi>Chief Justice,</hi> who having taken his <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation</hi> upon <hi>Oath,</hi> iſſu'd out <hi>Warrants,</hi> and ſo
<note n="*" place="margin">Lords, <hi>Powis, Arundel, Bellaſis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>three of the Lords</hi> (the <hi>Others,</hi> and moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> being in the <hi>Count<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97478:4"/>were ſecur'd that very night, or early next morning. The News flying pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently about, ſeveral of my <hi>Protestant Friends</hi> came to congratulate my want of <hi>Preferment,</hi> which they took as an infallible ſign of my Innocence; for they thought, I could not (if privy) have miſs'd of ſome <hi>Imployment,</hi> when <hi>Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourn</hi> a <hi>Player,</hi> and <hi>Townley</hi> an <hi>Alehouſe-keeper,</hi> were already eminently promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Within ſome hours after, I heard that the <hi>Earl of Powis</hi> and my <hi>Lord Arundel</hi> (for my <hi>Lord Bellaſis</hi> was not yet removed by reaſon of the <hi>Gout,</hi> which almoſt always afflicts him) were at the <hi>Gate-houſe,</hi> expecting how the <hi>Peers</hi> would diſpoſe of them; I went to ſee them, as my near Relation to the one, and my Acquaintance with the other, I thought, obliged me. There I found they were to lye that night, and ſo to be carried to the <hi>Tower,</hi> but little dreamed that I was immediately to ſucceed them; for Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> (for Reaſons beſt known to himſelf) thought fit next morning (<hi>viz. Friday</hi> the 25th.)
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oates</hi> accuſes me.</note> to accuſe me of <hi>Treaſon</hi> alſo to the <hi>Commons,</hi> who order'd the <hi>Juſtices
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97478:5"/>of Weſtminster</hi> (that were <hi>Members,</hi>) to examine him upon <hi>Oath,</hi> and then to proceed accordingly; which as ſoon as I heard, I went to take my leave of my <hi>Friends,</hi> foreſeeing that a <hi>Confinement</hi> would neceſſarily follow.</p>
            <p>Whilſt I was in my <hi>Viſits,</hi> one of my Servants came to acquaint me, that Mr. <hi>Tiſſard</hi> (the <hi>Sheriff</hi>) and his men were at my <hi>Houſe;</hi> ſo that returning home ſome few hours after, (to wit, about 10 at night) I found the Rooms below ſtairs full of <hi>People;</hi> and asking them for their <hi>Officer,</hi> I ſpoke to him to this effect; <hi>That I was ſorry I had made him ſtay ſo long, but that he needed not to have trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf with ſo many Attendants, ſince any one of them with Authority had been ſufficient.</hi> He anſwer'd, That by virtue of the <hi>Warrant,</hi> (which he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) <hi>he was to ſecure me and my Papers,</hi> but that he had not yet medled with them, becauſe he underſtood that I had the <hi>Keys</hi> of my <hi>Cabinets</hi> and <hi>Cloſet</hi> about me. I gave him many thanks for his Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility in not breaking open <hi>Locks</hi> unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, and then calling for Lights, I conducted him, and two or three of his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97478:5"/>Followers,
<note place="margin">He ſecures me and my Papers.</note> to my Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Having there ſeiz'd all my <hi>Papers,</hi> he ſealed them up in a <hi>Box</hi> with my own <hi>Arms,</hi> to avoid (as he told me) pretences of foul play, and ſo took it with him; but as for my ſelf, (being it was very late) he ſuffer'd me (at my requeſt) to lye at home with a Guard. In the morning he came again for me, and the <hi>Box</hi> being with him, I deſir'd, that ſince he had taken not only my <hi>Letters,</hi> but all ſorts of <hi>Papers</hi> alſo, as <hi>Bills, Acquittances, Accounts,</hi> and the like, (which might occaſion perhaps, I ſaid, ſome future diſpute between me and my <hi>Steward,</hi> or thoſe whom they concern'd) he would be pleas'd to let me ſee what he carried away. This too he civilly granted me; and when in the preſence of him and the reſt I had ſlightly viewed all, he ſealed the ſaid <hi>Box</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and then brought it and me (toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a <hi>Cabinet</hi> full of <hi>Deeds</hi> and <hi>Conveyances</hi>) (which I wonder'd not a little at,) to <hi>Sir Charles Harbord's,</hi> where I found not only <hi>Sir Charles,</hi> but <hi>Sir Philip Howard</hi> and <hi>Sir Edmund Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (the <hi>Knight-Marſhal</hi>) who came alſo thither to examine me.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97478:6"/>
            <p>When we were all ſeated about the Table,
<note place="margin">My Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>Sir Charles</hi> asked me, How long it was ſince my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Rome?</hi> I told him, <hi>I came last thence about the year</hi> 69. Then he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, Whether I was divorc'd? I anſwer'd, <hi>No</hi> Whether I knew one <hi>Strange?</hi> I told him, <hi>Yes.</hi> What was he for a man? I ſaid, <hi>He had been lately</hi> (as I heard) <hi>Provincial of the Jeſuits.</hi> Where had I ſeen him? I reply'd, <hi>Beyond Sea.</hi> Whether I had not ſeen him in <hi>England?</hi> I ſaid, <hi>Yes. When,</hi> continu'd he? I anſwer'd, I was not able to tell exactly, it being a good while ago. He deſir'd me to inform them as near as I could. I reply'd, That I thought at my <hi>return home</hi> (which was about that time twelve month, or a little more) he among others came to welcome me; but I was ſure I had not ſeen him in a long time. Then he asked me what I knew about the <hi>Plot?</hi> I anſwer'd, I knew <hi>nothing,</hi> neither did I believe there was any <hi>Plot.</hi> Did you (ſays he) never hear of any thing tending to a Deſign againſt the <hi>King?</hi> I anſwer'd, <hi>I never did in all my life,</hi> and that I thought my <hi>Relations
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97478:6"/>known Loyalty,</hi> and my <hi>Own,</hi> might aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them of it. <hi>If you had been made acquainted</hi> (ſays he) <hi>with a</hi> Deſign <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the</hi> King, <hi>do you think your ſelf bound to have diſcover'd it; and would you have done it?</hi> I anſwered, I was bound; and would have done it alſo.</p>
            <p>This is the <hi>ſum</hi> of my <hi>Examination;</hi> and as much of it as they deem'd fit, their <hi>Clerk</hi> (by their directions) put in writing, which I alſo read and ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. Now that the <hi>Reader</hi> may ſee the cauſe of all theſe Queſtions, I ſhall here inſert <hi>the particulars of</hi> Oats<hi>'s Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before the Commons,</hi> couch'd in his own Stile and Phraſe; And thus I found it (ſome few days after) in the very <hi>publick Papers</hi> that went about, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>That</hi> JAMES <hi>Earl of</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtlemain (for ſo he Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtned me) <hi>was, he verily believed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Oats<hi>'s Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>a</hi> Prieſt, <hi>and of the</hi> Order of Jeſus: <hi>That the ſaid</hi> Earl <hi>had ſued a</hi> Divorce <hi>between him and his Wife</hi> Barbara, <hi>now</hi> Dutcheſs <hi>of</hi> Cleveland, <hi>which</hi> Divorce, <hi>he</hi> (Oats) <hi>ſaw about</hi> November <hi>or</hi> December <hi>laſt, in the hands of</hi> Richard Strange, <hi>late</hi> Provincial <hi>of the</hi> Jeſuits <hi>in</hi> England;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97478:7"/>
                  <hi>and that in</hi> June <hi>or</hi> July <hi>last he heard the ſaid</hi> Earl <hi>in the Chamber of</hi> John Fenwick <hi>near the</hi> Horſe ſhoe <hi>in</hi> Drury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane, <hi>declare his Approbation of the late</hi> White-horſe-Conſult <hi>about the</hi> King's Death: <hi>preſent</hi> Baſil Langworth <hi>and the ſaid</hi> John Fenwick.</q>
            </p>
            <p>After Sir <hi>Charles</hi> had done with my <hi>Examination,</hi> he call'd for the <hi>Cabinet of Deeds;</hi> and taking out every <hi>Drawer,</hi> they opened ſome <hi>Parchments,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly thoſe with <hi>Great Seals;</hi> as <hi>Colledge-Leaſes, Exemplifications,</hi> &amp;c. So that to ſave trouble, I aſſur'd them there was nothing there beſides <hi>Writings</hi> relating to my <hi>Estate.</hi> Sir <hi>Charles</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>That among Writings it was a good place to hide Commiſſions:</hi> By which I found why the <hi>Sheriff</hi> had brought them away with him; And truly I think that Sir <hi>Charles</hi> did alſo ask me in my <hi>Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> about the ſo much diſcourſed of <hi>Commiſſions from Rome.</hi> Now for the ſealed <hi>Box of Papers,</hi> he commanded it to be carried up to his Chamber, ſaying it was to be ſent to the <hi>Council;</hi> And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we were riſen they ask'd the <hi>Sheriff</hi> ſeveral private Queſtions, which (by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97478:7"/>ſome words lowder than the reſt) I gueſs'd were concerning the manner of my ſurrendry, and the like.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> having thus fully performed their Duty, I told them I was not a little troubled, that my firſt Viſit to them ſhould be upon ſo ill, and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected an account; but ſince I had (as I hop'd) ſatisfi'd them in all particulars, I ſuppos'd I might now go home. Sir <hi>Charles</hi> anſwered, <hi>That they were to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the</hi> Houſe <hi>with what they had done, and that in the mean time the</hi> Sheriff <hi>was to keep me in cuſtody,</hi> who thereupon brought me to his <hi>Brother</hi>'s in <hi>Covent-Garden;</hi> but within few hours after Dinner, an <hi>Order</hi> came (ſigned by theſe, and the other <hi>Justices</hi>) to convey me to the <hi>Gate-houſe,</hi> from whence the <hi>Council</hi> ſent me afterwards by a <hi>Serjeant at Arms</hi> to the <hi>Tower.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sent to the</hi> Tower.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There I remained three <hi>months,</hi> that is to ſay, till the next Term; For on the firſt day of <hi>Hillary-Term,</hi> I moved for my <hi>Habeas corpus;</hi> and being brought by it to the <hi>King's Bench-Bar,</hi> the <hi>Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> asked Mr. Attorney <hi>Jones</hi> what he had to ſay againſt my Enlargement? He
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97478:8"/>anſwered, <hi>That I was a Priſoner (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared by my Commitment) for High Treaſon in the higheſt nature; but that he had but one Witneſs against me.</hi> My Caſe therefore being declared <hi>Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bailed</hi> Hil. Term 78.</note> I was bound in a Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of 2000 <hi>l.</hi> and my <hi>Sureties,</hi> which were <hi>two,</hi> in 1000 <hi>l.</hi> a piece, that I ſhould appear on the firſt of <hi>Eaſter Term,</hi> following.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>I appeared</hi> Eaſt. Term, 1679.</note> This I punctually performed; and at the end of the ſaid <hi>Term</hi> I was again orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to appear on the firſt of <hi>Trinity Term,</hi> which I did too; As alſo on the laſt of it; but then my <hi>Council,</hi> (to wit, Mr. <hi>Scroggs</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sanders) mov'd for my Diſcharge;</hi>
               <note place="margin">A motion in <hi>Trin. Term.</hi> 79.</note> So that Mr. <hi>Attorney</hi> (being call'd upon) anſwer'd, That Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> was my <hi>Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer,</hi> and if their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> pleas'd, they might know of him what he had againſt me. Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> preſently appeared, and openly averr'd, in my preſence, and in the face of the whole Court,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Oats</hi>'s Accuſation before the Judges of the <hi>Kings Bench.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That I had aſſented to the Death of the King: That I had ſued out a Divorce from</hi> Rome; <hi>which Divorce he ſaw in the hands of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97478:8"/>Provincial</hi> Strange; <hi>And that he belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved I was a</hi> Prieſt. Tho' this were only my firſt Accuſation; yet being of that high nature, the <hi>Court</hi> would not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge me;
<note place="margin">I appear in <hi>Mich. Term</hi> 1679.</note> therefore they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd me on Bail to appear on the firſt of <hi>Michaelmas Term;</hi> as I did; And then I was remitted to the laſt day of it, after the former man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: But long before that, there happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed another Adventure, which I am here to relate.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Saturday November</hi> 1. 1679.
<note place="margin">Taken the ſecond time.</note> I dined with my Lord <hi>Powis</hi> at the <hi>Tower;</hi> and about 5 in the evening, as I was coming from ſeeing my Lord <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> (who had been ill) ſome of my Lord <hi>Stafford</hi>'s people mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me, ſaid, That all the <hi>Gates</hi> were ſhut, and that the <hi>Gentleman Porter,</hi> with a <hi>Guard,</hi> was in queſt of me. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently deſired them to tell him he might find me at their <hi>Lords;</hi> which being done, an <hi>Order of Council</hi> was ſhown me by a <hi>Meſſenger;</hi> who alſo told me, That I muſt preſently attend the <hi>Board,</hi> So that calling for two <hi>Hackney-Coaches,</hi> (for they kept my own behind, to ſearch
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97478:9"/>it for Papers) they firſt carried me home; where I found another <hi>Meſſenger,</hi> wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching my Appartment, till I came my ſelf to open the doors Here they ſeiz'd on all my Papers; and from thence I was brought to the <hi>Lobby,</hi> and after ſome ſtay there, unto the <hi>Council-chamber</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Having made a low Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to the <hi>King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Brought before the King and Council and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined.</note> I ſtood not far from his <hi>Chair;</hi> then the Chancellor roſe up and asked me if I knew one <hi>Willoughby?</hi> I anſwered, <hi>Yes:</hi> How long have you known him ſaid he? I replied, <hi>I would (if his Lordſhip thought fit) give him an account, not only of that, but of every thing elſe within my knowledge concerning him,</hi> which he and the Board liking, I began thus; <hi>That one Mrs.</hi> Cellier <hi>viſiting the Priſons in the beginning of the Troubles, and coming to me (as ſhe did to others) about Charity for the poor there: I told her, I would not only then give her ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but would allow them weekly alſo: And thus</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>my Lords, I ſtill do. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this account</hi> (continued I) <hi>and that of the St.</hi> Omers <hi>Witneſſes, (which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97478:9"/>I had provided for my own Defence in caſe of Trial, and which I lodged at her Houſe) ſhe came frequently to me; and (among the news and accidents of the Priſons) told me one day, ſhe had taken out of</hi> New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, <hi>for</hi> 3 l. 10 s. <hi>a young man verst a little in the Law, whom ſhe thought very fit to look after ſeveral deſperate Debts (to the value of</hi> 3 <hi>or</hi> 4000 l.) <hi>due to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, who had formerly been a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> French-<hi>merchant: This Fellow was, it ſeems,</hi> Willoughby, <hi>now</hi> Dangerfield: <hi>and him ſhe ſent ſometimes to my Houſe on ordinary Errands; but preſently he plaid me as villanous a trick as could be imagin'd, conſidering the times we live in; the thing was this; The five</hi> Jeſuits <hi>being</hi> (<hi>on the</hi> 20th. <hi>of</hi> June <hi>last</hi>) <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he came within very few days after, to me, either in my Lady</hi> Powis<hi>'s Name, or pretending to go to her afterwards, and asked me if I thought it convenient to have their Speeches printed: I told him, By all means; for why ſhould ſuch excellent and loyal things fall to the ground? He replied,</hi> That it would coſt <hi>Ten pound; Well, ſaid I, if it does, tell my Lady I'l willingly give ſomething towards it;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97478:10"/>and ſo he departed. Not long after, I went to the</hi> Tower <hi>to ſee my Lord; and as ſoon as I met him, ſaid he, (with an apparent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfaction)</hi> Why did you ſend a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to me? And beſides, what have I to do with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Speeches? <hi>Has any body (anſwer'd I) been with you in my Name concerning that Affair?</hi> Yes, <hi>(re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied he)</hi> one <hi>Willoughby</hi> (as they call'd him) whom I ſent away as he came, as ſoon as he acquainted me with the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. <hi>This accident ſurprizing and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling me not a little, I took my leave of his Lordſhip, aſsuring him that I never ſent the Fellow, and ſo went ſtraight to Mrs.</hi> Celli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, (<hi>who being hunted for by Sir</hi> William Waller <hi>and Captain</hi> Richardſon, <hi>lay then at</hi> Powis-houſe) <hi>and bidding the Porter call her to me, I acquainted her what the Spark had done; and alſo told her, He was ſo great a Villain, that if ever he came any more to me, I would order my Servants to kick him out of my Houſe. Thus, my Lord,</hi> (ſaid I to the <hi>Chancellor</hi>) <hi>you have an account of my acquaintaince with</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby, <hi>and the reaſon alſo I had to be angry, and to forbid him for ever coming near me again.</hi> But (anſwer'd the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor</hi>)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97478:10"/>did you never know of any <hi>Propoſal</hi> made to him by the <hi>Lords in the Tower? No,</hi> ſaid I. Nor were you (proceeds his <hi>Lordſhip</hi>) ever angry with him <hi>for refuſing to perform what they propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to him? No</hi> (replied I) <hi>I aſſure your Lordſhips.</hi> Mr. <hi>Willoughby</hi> (ſays the <hi>Chancellor</hi>) you may perchance refreſh my <hi>Lord</hi>'s memory with particular cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. Upon which he appeared on the other ſide of the <hi>Table,</hi> being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with his <hi>Keeper</hi> in a corner, unſeen by me; and making a bow, I am behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (ſaid he) to your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming ſo material a part of my <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. As how, good Mr.</hi> Willoughby, anſwered I? That I was (ſaid he) with the <hi>Lords</hi> in the <hi>Tower. But Sir,</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered I) <hi>did I not, after your going thus thither in my Name, forbid you from co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming at me any more?</hi> You did, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red he, and <hi>it was the laſt time I came. Then make, I pray, what advantage you can,</hi> ſaid I. The <hi>Lords</hi> in the <hi>Tower</hi> (continues he) having made me the <hi>propoſal,</hi> I crav'd time to conſider of it, which did not a little diſpleaſe them; And when I went next to my <hi>Lord Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stlemain</hi>'s,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97478:11"/>I found him in his <hi>Study;</hi> who, as ſoon as he perceived me, roſe up in anger, and asked me, <hi>Why I would not do that which the Lords propoſed to me, and for which I was taken out of</hi> Priſon? So that, finding his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> in paſſion, <hi>I ran down ſtairs, and went away. Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> affirming this, and I the contrary, <hi>viz. That I never heard of any</hi> Propoſal <hi>made him by the Lords;</hi> The <hi>Chancellor</hi> ſaid, He would tell me what the <hi>Propoſal</hi> was, to make me the better call the whole buſineſs to mind; and then declar'd, <hi>That they had propos'd the Killing of the King to him;</hi> and this alſo <hi>Willoughby</hi> atteſted. <hi>I know nothing of it,</hi> replied I; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon asked <hi>Willoughby when it was that I thus frighted him down ſtairs?</hi> As he was muſing a while, and looking up in a conſidering poſture, I ſaid, <hi>You had need Friend conſider well for it is the</hi> Queſtion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout time <hi>is the thing that will ever confound you and ſuch as you are.</hi> At laſt he told me; It was a fortnight or three weeks after Sir <hi>Geo. Wakeman</hi>'s Trial. <hi>Now, my</hi> Lords, (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied I) <hi>I have all I deſire, having caught him (as I expected) in a most evident</hi> Lie <hi>and</hi> Contradiction; <hi>for did he not confeſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97478:11"/>to your Lordſhips, that he never came to me after his</hi> Knavery <hi>at the</hi> Tower <hi>which was</hi> (<hi>as appears by the publick ſale of the</hi> Jeſuits Speeches) <hi>at leaſt</hi> five weeks <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir</hi> George Wakeman<hi>'s Trial; and yet now he affirms,</hi> That my being angry with him was even a fortnight or three weeks after the ſaid Trial. This ſo much ſtartled him, that he had nothing to ſay, but that he would ſhew me circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to prove the Truth of his Allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which were, That I was then wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Compendium,</hi> a <hi>Paragraph</hi> of which he read as it lay before me on the <hi>Table:</hi> That one <hi>Lawſon</hi> was then in the Houſe, as alſo <hi>Turner</hi> the <hi>Booksel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. Theſe (ſaid I) are vain things, and ſo far from reconciling your former</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, <hi>that they create new ones; For how was it poſſible for you to read a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph in a Paper, when I my ſelf was by, and (as you urge)</hi> in an angry humour, <hi>at the very first ſight of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[And here I muſt, with my <hi>Reader</hi>'s leave, further acquaint him, That <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield</hi> neither pretended to have done this by ſurprize, nor would it have avai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, had he ſaid ſo; for my <hi>Chair</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97478:12"/>and <hi>Table</hi> in my <hi>Study,</hi> (as every one of my Servants knew, and as the very <hi>Officers</hi> that had newly ſearch'd it could witneſs) ſo face the door, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any body to come in, and not to be preſently ſeen by me, when there.] Now (continu'd I to <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi>) for the perſons you name, they are eaſily gueſs'd at, <hi>Lawſon</hi> being my <hi>Sollicitor,</hi> and conſequently moſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings with me, and the other my <hi>Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller,</hi> who having Orders to bring me ſtill whatſoever was new, could not but be often at my Houſe, the <hi>Preſs</hi> being at preſent ſo prolifick. He to amuſe me and the <hi>Board,</hi> began again with the <hi>Compendium,</hi> and that he read only part of a <hi>Paragraph;</hi> but the <hi>Chancellor</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, that that was not the preſent Queſtion, he was ſent out, and <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> came in,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oates</hi> came in againſt me.</note> who had not long before written in a <hi>Note</hi> that he had ſomething to accuſe me of.</p>
            <p>As he was going to ſpeak, the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor</hi> commanded the <hi>Clerk</hi> to give him his <hi>Oath. Mr. Oates</hi> anſwer'd, he had already ſworn to what he had there to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97478:12"/>ſay. If you have ſworn a thouſand times, (reply'd <hi>his Lordſhip</hi>) no body here will believe you, unleſs you ſwear alſo before them. Upon that he kiſſed the <hi>Book</hi> without more words, and then ſaid;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oates</hi>'s his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation before the King and Council.</note> 
               <hi>That he ſaw me at a Meeting, in which I appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Deſign of killing the King; That I had ſued out a Divorce in the Court of</hi> Rome <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and the Dutcheſs of</hi> Cleveland, <hi>which Divorce he ſaw in the hands of Mr.</hi> Strange <hi>the then Provincial; and that he had alſo ſeen Letters both from</hi> Liege <hi>and</hi> Rome (if I forget not) <hi>that I was a Prieſt and had ſaid Maſs.</hi> I aſſured their <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> that I would not tell them a <hi>Lye</hi> upon any account whatſoever; and if they found me thus guilty in the leaſt particular, I deſired that all things laid to my charge might be believed. Then I told them as for my being a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> I ſhould (were I one) be ſo far from po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively denying it, as I did, that I would glory in the <hi>Title;</hi> but for the <hi>Divorce</hi> I durſt appeal to the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> her ſelf, whom he had named. The <hi>Chancellor</hi> reply'd ſuddenly to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97478:13"/>That the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> would ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the wrong or prejudice of any body. <hi>My Lord,</hi> (anſwer'd I) I ſpeak not this reflectingly, but to acquaint you, that ſhe (who is concern'd, and who has I am ſure made much enquiry about it) does certainly know the falſity of it. Then I deſir'd their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> to conſider, whether it were poſſible, that ſuch a ſilly pitiful Fellow as <hi>Oates,</hi> ſhould have thus all <hi>Catholicks Secrets</hi> (let their <hi>Quality</hi> be what it would) communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him. But as I was in this manner deſcanting on my Accuſer, a <hi>Lord</hi> roſe up and told me, <hi>That I muſt know I was in the King's preſence, and that I was not to give his Witneſſes foul language,</hi> with much more to that effect. So after ſome further Velitations with Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and that I had aſſur'd him, I ſhould at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, and in another place, ſhew him fully his miſtakes, and particularly about the <hi>Divorce,</hi> (which I ſaid ſeveral <hi>Letters</hi> of mine taken from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſtill in the hands of the <hi>Council</hi> would clear) he went out; but before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtirred, I addreſs'd my ſelf to the <hi>King</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe or the like words: <q rend="margQuotes">That tho'
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97478:13"/>my <hi>Innocence</hi> hindred me from fearing the puniſhment of a <hi>Traytor,</hi> yet I could not but deem my ſelf extreamly unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in being accuſed of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> when I had from time to time (as his <hi>Majeſty</hi> well knew) given all the marks imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of my <hi>Loyalty.</hi> I ask'd alſo the <hi>Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s pardon for ſaying any thing that offended him or the <hi>Board,</hi> &amp; ſo retir'd.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Many other things I had to urge to the <hi>Council;</hi> as their great diſ-eſteem and ſlight (hardly three days before) of <hi>Dangerfield</hi>'s Teſtimony againſt <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel Manſel;</hi> his not laying to my charge any <hi>Treaſon;</hi> for he accuſed me not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively of knowing what the <hi>Lords</hi> in the <hi>Tower</hi> had propoſed to him; and that as for <hi>Mr. Oates</hi>'s Charge, I had been impriſon'd for it, and was then actually upon <hi>Bail.</hi> I ſay, I had many things to urge of this nature, which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd till I ſhould be again called in; for I thought I was to be clear'd or ſentenc'd <hi>vivâ voce</hi> by the <hi>Board.</hi> But after an hours waiting, <hi>Sir Tho. Doleman</hi> told me, the <hi>Lords</hi> were riſen,
<note place="margin">Sent to the <hi>Tower</hi> the ſecond time.</note> and that there was an <hi>Order</hi> drawing to commit me for <hi>High-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97478:14"/>to the <hi>Tower,</hi> where I was next day carried by <hi>Serjeant Beck,</hi> it being then near 10 at night.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Particulars of my 2d. <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> and in them I have been the more fuſe, to ſhew how far from any favour the <hi>Lords of the Privy-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> ſtill were, for tho' in my <hi>Caſe</hi> there appear'd matter enough to juſtifie ſome Indulgence, had they pleaſed, yet they deem'd it fitter for me to undergo the trouble of a new Confinement, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the <hi>Objections</hi> againſt the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi>) than that there ſhould be (by their means,) the leaſt poſſibility for an accuſed <hi>Papiſt</hi> to eſcape. But for all this conſtant practice of theirs, <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> has not been wanting upon ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, in publickly taxing the <hi>Board</hi> of Partiality on our behalf.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as I was brought to the <hi>Tower,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Some Accidents in the <hi>Tower.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mr. Cheek</hi> (the preſent <hi>Lieutenant</hi>) made me a <hi>cloſe Priſoner,</hi> whereby not only my <hi>Friends,</hi> but my very <hi>Servants,</hi> except a <hi>Valet de Chambre,</hi> were deny'd acceſs. On the <hi>Wedneſday-night</hi> following, (<hi>viz. Nov.</hi> 5.) the <hi>Gentleman-Jaylor</hi> came to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97478:14"/>me for the <hi>Lieutenants Fee;</hi> I anſwer'd, That if the <hi>Fee</hi> were precarious, and at the Priſoner's Will, (as I had often heard it was) the asking of it now, I thought, was ill timed, for one Courteſie deſerv'd another; and then I deſir'd to know the reaſon of this ſevere Confinement, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when the <hi>Warrant,</hi> ſhown me by the <hi>Serjeant at Arms,</hi> mentioned only <hi>Safe-cuſtody,</hi> which is the <hi>Liberty of the Tower</hi> in other terms. He anſwer'd, That the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> did ſtill upon the receit of a <hi>Priſoner,</hi> attend the <hi>King,</hi> to know his Commands, and accordingly he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards acted. I reply'd, <hi>Sir John Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon</hi> follow'd his <hi>written Orders;</hi> and then further told him, that as for the Money required of me, I was ſo far at all times from denying an <hi>Officer</hi> his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted <hi>Fee,</hi> that I deem'd it as much his due as his Rents, ſeeing otherwiſe an <hi>Imployment</hi> would not be ſuch a favour as 'twas deſign'd; ſo that to ſave him trouble for the future, he was to know, that I had already paid it. To whom, anſwer'd he? To <hi>Sir John Robinſon,</hi> (reply'd I,) the former <hi>Lieutenant;</hi> for ſince there can be but one <hi>Fee</hi> due for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97478:15"/>any one <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> and ſince being out only upon <hi>Bail,</hi> I had been ſtill the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Priſoner</hi> as much as ever, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having paid it to <hi>Sir John, Mr. Cheek</hi> could no more demand any thing of me, than of any other <hi>Lord</hi> in the <hi>Tower.</hi> But (continu'd I,) I ſhall ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly inform both his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Mr. Lieutenant</hi>'s Arbitrary uſage, contrary to their expreſs <hi>Orders,</hi> and if they approv'd it, I ſhould do the like alſo; In the mean time pray tell him of it, and bring me the <hi>Copy</hi> of my <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment</hi> at your next coming. <hi>Mr. Lieutenant</hi> (ſays he) is not now at home; but as he was going away, I told him, that leſt any miſtake ſhould happen in the Meſſage, (for now adays I ſaw miſtakes in every thing,) I would write it down, as I preſently did, and ſo read it to him in my <hi>man's</hi> hearing. Next day, I prepared a <hi>Petition</hi> for the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> and at night I asked him again for my ſaid <hi>Commitment.</hi> He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, That the <hi>Clerk</hi> ſhould have brought it, had he not been abroad all day, and therefore he begg'd my pardon till the morning; but failing of it then
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97478:15"/>alſo, I ſent my <hi>Man</hi> towards noon to demand it of the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> himſelf, who ſaid, That his <hi>Clerk</hi> ſhould forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with bring it, which he never did till the night following, which was <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day;</hi> and then I ſent him back with it, telling him, I had been put off too long, and that my <hi>Sollicitor</hi> ſhould call, when he lack'd it.</p>
            <p>Some were of opinion that Mr. <hi>Cheek</hi> did thus confine me till <hi>Saturday,</hi> (which was the 7th. day) and delay the ſending a Copy of my <hi>Commitment,</hi> on purpoſe that I ſhould loſe the advantage of the <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpus Act,</hi> which obliges the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> either to <hi>Bail</hi> or a <hi>Trial,</hi> if it be prayed in the firſt <hi>week</hi> of the <hi>Term.</hi> But whatever the <hi>Lieutenant</hi>'s motives were, he brought himſelf within the <hi>Penalty</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Act;</hi> for it expreſly declares, <hi>That the non-delivery of the</hi> Copy <hi>of a</hi> Commitment <hi>within ſix hours demand, is the forfeiture of one hundred pounds to the Priſoner; and the ſecond</hi> Conviction, <hi>the loſs of his very Office or Employment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' the Clerk (as I ſaid) brought me not the <hi>Commitment</hi> till <hi>Saturday-night,</hi> yet <hi>Mr. Cheek</hi> came to ſee me in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97478:16"/>morning, and then acquainted me, that in anſwer to my <hi>Petition,</hi> the <hi>Liberty of the Tower</hi> was granted by the <hi>Board;</hi> that he hoped I would not take that little <hi>Confinement</hi> unkindly at his hands, it being his duty, he thought, to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>King</hi> after his receiving of a <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner,</hi> to know fully his pleaſure; and that if he had erred in the not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſtrict words of an <hi>Order,</hi> his being ſo ſhort a time in the place might very reaſonably plead his excuſe; nor was it (he aſſur'd me) his temper to be uneaſie or troubleſome to any under his <hi>Charge;</hi> for he could live (he ſaid) without the leaſt Diſpute his whole life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time with men of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Worth,</hi> and ſo named my <hi>Lord Arundel,</hi> my <hi>Lord Bellaſis,</hi> and <hi>Sir Henry Titchborn,</hi> &amp;c. I anſwer'd, That kind uſage was at leaſt the interpreting <hi>Orders</hi> in the beſt ſence, and not in the worſt; that the <hi>Order</hi> was ſo plain, that it was impoſſible (one would have thought) to miſtake it, but that my greateſt trouble was, that <hi>Mr. Cheek</hi> (whom I had long known and been acquainted with) ſhould deal more ſeverely with me, than a <hi>Stranger;</hi> yet
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97478:16"/>ſince I was his <hi>Priſoner,</hi> he ſhould find as much Complyance and Civility from me as from any man in the <hi>Tower.</hi> To this he made a courteous Reply, and then asked me about the <hi>Cauſe of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Restraint,</hi> which when I had told him, with all the Particulars already mention'd, he took his leave; nor am I certain whether he ſaid any thing about his <hi>Fee;</hi> but if he did, I ſhewed him again the Reaſons of my diſputing it, as I had done before by his <hi>Officer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having now the ſatisfaction of ſeeing my <hi>fellow-Priſoners</hi> and other <hi>Friends,</hi> I thought fit to uſe the means (which the <hi>Law</hi> provided) for my <hi>Liberty,</hi> and therefore towards the end of the <hi>Term,</hi> (for having not the advantage of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, all parts of it were alike) I moved for my <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I brought my <hi>Habeas Corp</hi> 72/80.</note> and ſo was brought on <hi>Friday</hi> the 21ſt. to the <hi>King's-Bench.</hi> The <hi>Judges</hi> asked me, What I deſired? My <hi>Councel</hi> anſwer'd, To be <hi>Bail'd.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Mr. Attorney Levins</hi> was ſent for, who ſaid, <hi>That I was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for High-Treaſon, (as appear'd by my Commitment) and that I now had another
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97478:17"/>Witneſs againſt me.</hi> I anſwer'd, That the new one had not laid <hi>Treaſon</hi> to my Charge, and that I hoped ſince the <hi>Court</hi> was ſo favourable formerly as to bail me upon a <hi>Commitment of High-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the higheſt nature,</hi> they would do the like now, when it ſpecifi'd <hi>High-Treaſon</hi> only. The <hi>Judges</hi> reply'd, That it was not (they thought) within their power. Then <hi>my Lords</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand my Tryal.</hi> Do you hear <hi>Mr. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney</hi> (anſwer'd the <hi>Ch. Juſtice</hi>) what my <hi>Lord</hi> ſays, He demands his <hi>Tryal?</hi> This ſeem'd to ſurprize a great many, for it was the firſt time that any body had called for <hi>Tryal,</hi> ſince the ſtirs about the <hi>Plot;</hi> and <hi>Mr. Sanders</hi> hearing my Requeſt, moved, <hi>that it might be recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Sir Francis Pemberton</hi> (out of Charity I ſuppoſe to an old Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance and Client) reply'd, Do you know <hi>Mr. Sanders</hi> what you ask? would you have a <hi>Tryal recorded</hi> about <hi>Treaſon,</hi> when there are two <hi>Witneſſes</hi> ready to prove it? <hi>My Lords,</hi> (ſaid I to the Court) my coming hither was principally for <hi>Bail,</hi> which I humbly conceive your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> may legally grant; Therefore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97478:17"/>be pleas'd to order me a <hi>Rule,</hi> that I may again wait upon you, when you have conſider'd my Caſe more through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than your preſent great buſineſs will perchance give you leave. This I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd at laſt, and ſo returned to the <hi>Tower;</hi> but before <hi>Wedneſday</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (which was the day I intended to appear again) there happen'd this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, which put me out of all hopes of ſucceſs in my buſineſs.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Oats,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An Accident.</note> ſince his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, had two men call'd <hi>Lane</hi> and <hi>Osborn,</hi> who inform'd one <hi>Knox</hi> (a late Servant to the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi>) that their <hi>Maſter</hi> had made a <hi>Sodomitical At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> on the Body of the ſaid <hi>Lane;</hi> whereupon <hi>Knox</hi> encouraged them to bring the Affair upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> as they did; But within a while after they were Indicted, <hi>for maliciouſly conſpiring to blaſt the Kings Fvidence,</hi> &amp;c. And their <hi>Trial</hi> happened on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 25<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> being the day that juſt preceded my aforeſaid intended ſecond Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Theſe not being found compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to cope with Mr. <hi>Oats,</hi> to make their <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> plain and indiſputable, had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97478:18"/>Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> as a Witneſs againſt them. His <hi>Evidence</hi> brought up the Rear, and lay heavieſt on <hi>Catholicks,</hi> for he made them the main Contrivers of this buſineſs, tho' before the ſtorm fell on my <hi>Lord Danby,</hi> as may be ſeen in the Printed <hi>Trial. Dangerfield</hi> having thus a large Field to ſport in, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I was again ſhortly to appear in that very <hi>Court</hi> about <hi>Bail,</hi> depoſed, <hi>That the Affidavits or Charge againſt</hi> Oats (<hi>which</hi> Lane <hi>had ſworn to) had been ſent from the</hi> Tower <hi>to one Mr.</hi> Nevil <hi>(a Proteſtant) and to me, to enlarge upon as we ſhould think fit.</hi> This being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently all about the <hi>Town,</hi> ſeveral of my <hi>Friends</hi> adviſed me not to ſtir any more that <hi>Term;</hi> but I told them I muſt beg their Pardon; for tho' the <hi>Judges</hi> might perchance be now loſs favourable and indulgent; yet I would never counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance a <hi>falſe Accuſation</hi> ſo far as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt for it, from doing what I had pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly declared before.
<note place="margin">Second Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance.</note> I went therefore to the <hi>Hall</hi> as I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd; but finding it order'd, (by reaſon of a long Cauſe, or ſome buſineſs of that nature) <hi>That no perſon who came by their</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97478:18"/>Habeas Corpus, <hi>ſhould be that day heard,</hi> I thought it not amiſs to have my <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel</hi> acquaint the <hi>Court,</hi> that I had been there, and then to demand a new <hi>Rule</hi> for <hi>Friday;</hi> which being granted, I appeared accordingly,
<note place="margin">Third Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> and found the <hi>Judges</hi> (as I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected) ſeverer than uſually; for <hi>Mr. Justice Dolben</hi> told me even at firſt to this purpoſe; <hi>That I might have ſpared my pains, they having heard (ſince my last being there) ſtrange things of me.</hi> And my <hi>Lord Ch. Juſtice</hi> ſaid, <hi>That I had (it ſeems) made ſo ill uſe of my late Liberty, and of the favour of the Court, that it would be the worſe, he believed, for others.</hi> After I had heard this and more to the ſame effect, I told their <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> that none could hinder the tongue of an ill man; that I would anſwer when they pleas'd to any Charge; and that in the mean time, I hop'd, they would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny me my <hi>Liberty</hi> upon <hi>Bail,</hi> ſeeing my <hi>Commitment was for High-Treaſon only.</hi> At this ſome of the ſtanders by repeated the words <hi>for High-Treaſon only,</hi> with no little <hi>Emphaſis</hi> and wonder. <hi>My Lords,</hi> (ſaid I) 'tis not that I think <hi>High-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:97478:19"/>a ſlight and inſufficient accuſation, but I uſe the word <hi>Only,</hi> as ſome induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to you to grant my Requeſt, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring you, as I did t'other day, <hi>that I was bail'd, when my Commitment mention'd High-Treaſon in the higheſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> and therefore I cannot doubt of leſs favour now, that it runs in a more ſoft and gentle phraſe. Beſides (conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu'd I) give me leave to acquaint your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> that my <hi>Councel</hi> are of opinion, that I have the <hi>Law</hi> on my ſide. It is ſtrange your <hi>Councel</hi> ſhould tell you ſo, reply'd the <hi>Ch. Juſtice.</hi> My Lord (ſays <hi>Mr. Sanders</hi> to me) your <hi>Sollicitor</hi> has I ſuppoſe wrongly inform'd you; and then <hi>Mr. Scroggs</hi> turning to me, deſir'd I would name the <hi>Councel.</hi> This Anſwer of theirs a little ſurprized me; for I thought a <hi>Lawyer</hi> that takes a <hi>Fee,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes me to proceed as I propoſe, if he forbids it not, according to the common <hi>Axiom, Qui non vetat, cum potest, jubet.</hi> I ſpeak not this with any reflexion on theſe <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> but to ſhow how high the ſtorm was, when <hi>Lawyers</hi> themſelves fear'd to countenance their <hi>Clients,</hi> if their <hi>Caſe</hi> ſeem'd in the leaſt dubious or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97478:19"/>diſguſtful. Deſiring then no Diſputes with my own <hi>Councel,</hi> I addreſt my ſelf to the <hi>Judges,</hi> and after they had again told me, that my Requeſt could not be granted, I ſaid, I was ſorry that I had been forced thus to trouble them; that I knew they would pardon it, ſince that <hi>excellent Court</hi> was the only place, which men in my <hi>preſent condition</hi> were to fly to; that I ſhould always acknowledge with a great ſenſe, the favours I had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten received of their <hi>Lordſhips;</hi> that I did acquieſce in their Judgment, and could now with ſatisfaction go back to priſon, having perform'd the duty which I thought my ſelf obliged to; that I hop'd no misfortune of mine would be a prejudice to others; And laſtly, I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated them to remember, <hi>that I did again and again demand Tryal;</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly innocent, I would not wave it, were there as many ſuch Witneſſes againſt me as could ſtand between <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> and the <hi>Tower.</hi> Their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> received what I ſaid very civilly, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding again, that they were ſorry they could not relieve me, and ſo I preſently return'd.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:97478:20"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fees again demanded.</note> Some few nights after the <hi>Gentleman-Gaoler</hi> came again to me in <hi>Mr. Lieutenant's</hi> Name for his <hi>Fee.</hi> I anſwer'd, I thought I had already ſatisfi'd him in that point; but if it were otherwiſe, I could not help it, for I had no more to ſay. He repli'd to this effect, That the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> would uſe means, he believ'd, to have it, and locking the doors, departed. Next morning I was hardly dreſt, when one of my men came and told me, that the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> paſſing by had called for the <hi>Warder,</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently returned with this Order; <hi>That for the future he was to be in the Room when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I gave or received Viſits:</hi> I bade him do his duty, for it was equal to me who heard my diſcourſe; but I would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs ſhortly know by what Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <hi>Mr. Cheek</hi> dealt thus with me. Therefore as ſoon as the <hi>Council</hi> ſate, I ſent a <hi>Petition</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> in which I ſhewed them what <hi>Mr. Cheek</hi> had done; and withal, that it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary not only to the practice of the <hi>Tower,</hi> but to their own late poſitive Commands; that his pretence for his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary proceeding was, becauſe I refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97478:20"/>him thoſe <hi>Fees,</hi> which I had already paid, and ſo I ſtated my <hi>Caſe.</hi> I added further, That ſuppoſing I had been his <hi>Debtor,</hi> yet I knew that that <hi>illustrious Board</hi> would never ſuffer them who had the charge of <hi>Priſoners,</hi> to be their own <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Carvers.</hi> This was publickly read, but the <hi>King</hi> thought fit not to order any thing thereupon; for there happen'd alſo at the ſame time other <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions</hi> about <hi>Fees;</hi> and his <hi>Majesty</hi> (as I was informed) had hints before-hand, how prejudicial it would be to his <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi> if he countenanc'd thoſe that refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the paying of them. But tho' he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd nothing (as I ſaid) in this Affair, yet, I believe, the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd to be a little careful of what he did; for he ſeemed afterwards not ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous as in the beginning; and truly (for my own part) I thought, by this his more civil carriage, he was convinc'd that I had Right on my ſide, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently that he would not purſue the buſineſs any further.</p>
            <p>Within a while after,
<note place="margin">1679/80.</note> 
               <hi>Hilary Term</hi> began, and asking then the <hi>opinion</hi> of ſome <hi>Friends,</hi> what I had beſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97478:21"/>do; they told me, That I had ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquainted the <hi>Court</hi> with my deſire of <hi>Tryal;</hi> that doubtleſs the <hi>King's Council</hi> had already reſolved whom to <hi>try</hi> and whom to <hi>bail;</hi> that it would perchance diſguſt them to be further preſſed by me, becauſe it might ſhock and interfere with their preſent meaſures; that my beſt way was therefore to expect their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and that certainly I ſhould in courſe be either ſuddenly brought to <hi>Bar,</hi> or <hi>bail'd.</hi> I was no way averſe to this <hi>Advice,</hi> knowing that if the worſt came to the worſt, the following <hi>Term</hi> (being that of <hi>Eaſter</hi>) would put me <hi>in ſtatu quo;</hi> and truly I found no help till then. Therefore reſolving to be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger behind-hand, I order'd my <hi>Councel</hi> to demand <hi>Tryal</hi> on the very firſt day of the ſaid <hi>Term,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eaſter</hi> Term, 1680.</note> and to have it <hi>recorded</hi> alſo. This was done accordingly, and on the laſt of it, (my <hi>Bill</hi> being found by the <hi>Grand-Jury</hi>) I was to be try'd or ſet at liberty in <hi>Trinity Term,</hi> which beginning within leſs than <hi>three weeks</hi> after, I thought it not worth the troubling of my ſelf or friends, to take the advantage of the <hi>late Act</hi> as to <hi>Bail</hi> in the mean while.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:97478:21"/>
            <p>When this <hi>Term</hi> came,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trin.</hi> Term, 80.</note> I was forc'd to a very unuſual trouble and charge, <hi>viz.</hi> to move for my <hi>Arraignment,</hi> and to pay for the <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> &amp;c. which brought me down. Now the reaſon why I thus preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on, was, becauſe if the day of my <hi>Tryal</hi> were not appointed, (which I knew could not, or would not be till I were <hi>arraign'd</hi>) ſeveral of my <hi>Witneſſes</hi> might fail me in coming to <hi>Town;</hi> and then if <hi>Mr. Attorney</hi> (at the latter end of the ſaid <hi>Term</hi>) ſhould tell me he was ready, <hi>I muſt either enter theſe Liſts</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd, or take it as a mighty favour to lye in <hi>Priſon</hi> till <hi>Michaelmas.</hi> So much then for the <hi>Preliminaries;</hi> and now for my <hi>Arraignment</hi> and <hi>Tryal.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section__trial">
               <head>My Arraignment and Tryal.</head>
               <p>ON <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 15th. of <hi>June,</hi> 1680.
<note place="margin">My Arraignment and Tryal.</note> I was <hi>arraign'd</hi> at the <hi>King's-Bench Bar, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to diſturb the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to kill the King, levy War, and alter
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97478:22"/>the eſtabliſh'd Religion to the Superstition of the Church of</hi> Rome; to which after I had pleaded <hi>Not Guilty,</hi> and put my ſelf upon my <hi>Countrey,</hi> I was remanded to the <hi>Tower, Wedneſday</hi> 23d. being appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for my <hi>Tryal.</hi> About 8 of the <hi>clock</hi> that day, I was again brought by <hi>Mr. Lieutenant</hi> to the ſame <hi>Bar,</hi> and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards 9 the <hi>Tryal</hi> began with the uſual <hi>Proclamations</hi> and Formalities. <hi>Sir John Cutler</hi> was <hi>Foreman</hi> of the <hi>Jury,</hi> and next to him <hi>Sir Reginald Foſter;</hi> but when <hi>Roger Jenyns of Hayes Eſq;</hi> was call'd, I acquainted the Judges, <hi>That that Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman was my near Relation, and that I left it to their Lordſhips to determine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould ſtand or no.</hi> The <hi>Court</hi> was well ſatisfi'd with this procedure, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating, that I depended (it ſeem'd) more on my <hi>Innocence</hi> than <hi>Friends,</hi> and ſo laying <hi>Mr. Jenyns</hi> aſide, <hi>Mr. Harriot</hi> ſucceeded. <hi>Mr. Cheney</hi> follow'd him; but upon <hi>Mr. Johnſon</hi>'s appearance, I ſaid to this effect; <hi>That tho' I had not hitherto challeng'd any body, yet I was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing that my Jury ſhould be compos'd wholly of ſuch as were interested in the late Attainders about the Plot; therefore to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97478:22"/>ſave their Lordſhips ſome time and trouble, I deſir'd them to order, that no more of thoſe Gentlemen ſhould be propos'd to me.</hi> The <hi>Ch. Justice</hi> anſwer'd, That it was the <hi>Priſoner's</hi> part, and not the <hi>Courts</hi> to except; therefore <hi>your Lordſhip</hi> muſt do it (ſays he) your ſelf, when you think you are aggriev'd. I repli'd, That I ſpoke not this reflectingly, and to ſhow alſo, that I had nothing particular againſt <hi>Mr. Johnſon,</hi> I was contented he ſhould ſtand, who thereupon took his <hi>Oath;</hi> nor did I make any further ſtop, only when two (who were often call'd) could not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly get into <hi>Court</hi> for the preſs, I bade the <hi>Clerk</hi> go on, the next on the <hi>Roll</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying their places; ſo that the <hi>twelve</hi> ſworn were theſe that follow:
<list type="jury_roster">
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sir John Cutler.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sir Regin. Foſter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Harriot</hi> Eſq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich. Cheney</hi> Eſq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Johnſon</hi> Eſq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joh. Roberts</hi> Eſq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Franc. Dorrington</hi> Eſq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hugh Squire</hi> Eſq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Charles Good</hi> Eſq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Pulford</hi> Eſq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Clayton</hi> Eſq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis Mayo</hi> Eſq;</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And here the</hi> Reader <hi>may already ſee how reſolv'd</hi> Combes,
<note place="margin">Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:97478:23"/>
                  <hi>the late</hi> Publiſher <hi>of my</hi> Tryal <hi>was, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it as diſadvantagious to me as he could, when he omits theſe Particulars even at the very Empanelling of the</hi> Jury; <hi>which of themſelves, (had they no relation to my Candour and Plain-dealing) were yet as fit to be mention'd as any other matter. Nor is he more ingenuous in the ſequel, for he ſtrangely mangles and lames as well the</hi> Evidence <hi>of</hi> my Witneſſes, <hi>as my</hi> own Anſwers; <hi>and to make the whole the more imperfect and obſcure, he leaves out, and confounds what he pleaſes all along;</hi> nay, <hi>to ſhow his falſhood almost in every thing, he makes</hi> Mr. Juſtice Raimond <hi>to ſpeak extreamly often, tho' he ſaid not one word to me all the while. This, I confeſs, may be yet gather'd by his</hi> Relation, <hi>that I was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most continually interrupted, ſo that it was ſtill with the utmost do, before I could bring any Argument or Inference to the least head. But truly I am not to wonder at the indirect way of publiſhing Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this nature, ſince every</hi> Tryal <hi>is complain'd of by thoſe that were preſent; and therefore, I think, beſides my own</hi> Notes, <hi>the early getting under their hands a full</hi> Account <hi>of what my</hi> Witneſſes <hi>have
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97478:23"/>attested, was no impertinent or over-cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Action. And thus,</hi> Reader, <hi>beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging pardon for the preſent Digreſſion, I ſhall now proceed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this, the <hi>Indictment</hi> was again read; and when the <hi>King's Councel,</hi> (viz. <hi>Mr. Attorney, Mr. Sollicitor, Sir George Jeoffries,</hi> and <hi>Sir Ir. Withens</hi>) had dilated on it, they call'd for <hi>Mr. Oates;</hi> but as I was about to ſpeak, I found two Difficulties therein; the one from the <hi>Auditory,</hi> who often deſir'd me <hi>to raiſe my voice;</hi> and the other from <hi>Mr. Attorney,</hi> who interrupting me, ſaid, <hi>It was not time yet;</hi> notwithſtanding I went on, what I ſpoke being to this purpoſe; <hi>That I had</hi> (<hi>as their</hi> Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips <hi>well knew by my often demanding</hi> Tryal) <hi>long wiſh'd for that happy day, as the ready means not only of obtaining my Liberty, but of ſhowing the World how much I had been calumniated and wronged; that I had pleaded</hi> Not Guilty, <hi>and now threw my ſelf into the Protection of that Excellent</hi> Court, and Seat of Juſtice, <hi>where I ſhould find (I was ſure) their</hi> Lordſhips <hi>as well my</hi> Councel <hi>as my</hi> Judges, <hi>and receive alſo of them all the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97478:24"/>Favours uſually granted</hi> Priſoners. <hi>Mr. Attorney</hi> interrupting me again, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had quite ended the laſt words; the <hi>Ch. Justice</hi> ask'd, <hi>If I had any thing againſt</hi> Mr. Oates; meaning (as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd) a legal Impediment, why he ſhould not be heard? I anſwer'd, <hi>No; but that I threw my ſelf into the Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Court, and was ready now to hear, what the</hi> Man <hi>had to ſay;</hi> whereupon he was ſworn, and then he accus'd me thus:</p>
               <p>That in the <hi>year</hi> 77.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr. Oate's</hi> Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> after his Negotiation for ſome months in <hi>Spain,</hi> (where he had ſeen <hi>Letters</hi> from me to the <hi>Fathers</hi> there) He, at his return home (in <hi>November</hi>) brought ſeveral <hi>Letters</hi> with him, and <hi>one</hi> among the reſt to me, the Contents of which he ſaw; That it expreſs'd, how zealous they of <hi>Spain</hi> were, in joyning with thoſe of <hi>England</hi> to carry on the <hi>Deſign;</hi> by which <hi>word,</hi> they even meant the <hi>King's Death,</hi> and <hi>bringing in Popery;</hi> that he deliver'd the ſaid <hi>Letter</hi> to <hi>Provincial Strange</hi> at <hi>London</hi> for me, and ſaw afterwards at <hi>St. Omers</hi> a <hi>Letter</hi> of mine, <hi>which (to his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97478:24"/>was the firſt he had ſeen;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n I acknowledg'd the receipt of that he brought me from <hi>Spain,</hi> and rejoyc'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the good opinion the <hi>Spaniſh Fathers</hi> had of me; that he (being privy to the <hi>Jeſuits Letters</hi>) ſaw alſo ſeveral others ſubſcrib'd ſometimes <hi>Palmer,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Caſtlemain,</hi> and own'd alſo for mine; that by and by he would give the <hi>Court</hi> an account how he knew my <hi>Hand;</hi> that in <hi>March</hi> there came another from me, which rejected the Advice of the <hi>Rectors of</hi> Liege <hi>and</hi> Gant; who deſir'd to have the <hi>Secular Clergie</hi> engag'd; <hi>for I thought them to be a looſe ſort of men, of no Principles, and conſequently unfit to be truſted.</hi> He further ſaid, (after ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Interrogations</hi> by the <hi>Court)</hi> that I was not, he thinks, at the <hi>great April Conſult,</hi> at leaſt he does not accuſe me of it, but that he ſaw me in <hi>May</hi> 78. at <hi>Wild-houſe,</hi> where he brought Meſſages to the <hi>Fathers;</hi> that I much deſir'd there an <hi>Aſſociation</hi> with the <hi>Benedictine Monks;</hi> that he knew me not then, nor could ſwear that I knew him, nor that there were any words about <hi>killing the King,</hi> or other <hi>Treaſon;</hi> yet he believes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97478:25"/>the Diſcourſe was bad enough; that on the 20<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of the following <hi>June,</hi> as he was going about 7 or 8 a <hi>clock</hi> in the <hi>Evening</hi> with <hi>Mr. Langworth,</hi> to drink a kind of Ale in <hi>Fuller</hi>'s <hi>Rents,</hi> which the ſaid <hi>Mr. Langworth</hi> lik'd, they met me in <hi>Lincolns-Inne-fields;</hi> that <hi>Mr. Langworth</hi> ſaluting me, recommended him the ſaid <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> as one ſerviceable in the preſent buſineſs; and alſo told him, who I was, <hi>bidding him take notice of me;</hi> that we went all to <hi>Mr. Fenwick's</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where they acquainted me with the Tranſactions of the <hi>April Conſult,</hi> in relation to the <hi>Death</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>introducing</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Religion;</hi> for <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> thinks, I did not know the Particulars of the <hi>Deſign</hi> before; Whereupon I ſaid openly to them, <hi>That now I ſhould be reveng'd for the Injuries done me.</hi> As for the manner how he came to know my <hi>Hand,</hi> it was (he ſaid) by ſeeing me then write the <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> of a <hi>Letter,</hi> which I gave him to carry to the <hi>general Poſt-houſe</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> it being about 11 at night; nor did he remember, that any body came in to us then at <hi>Mr. Fenwick</hi>'s, except the <hi>Maid</hi> that brought us <hi>Drink.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:97478:25"/>
               <p>Now towards the <hi>cloſe</hi> of the <hi>Charge,</hi> I began to ask <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> ſeveral Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for (in theſe <hi>Tryals</hi> about the <hi>Plot</hi>) the Accus'd were ſtill admoniſh'd to ſtay, till the <hi>Witneſs</hi> had finiſh'd his Evidence; but firſt I bade him repeat his <hi>Journey,</hi> which he did thus; <hi>That he went to</hi> Spain <hi>in</hi> Apr. 77. <hi>that he return'd in</hi> November; <hi>that about</hi> December <hi>he came to</hi> St. Omers, <hi>from whence in</hi> March <hi>he went to</hi> Liege, <hi>and in</hi> April (ſome few days before the <hi>Conſult</hi>) to <hi>London. When you met me (ſaid I) in</hi> Lincolns-Inn-fields) <hi>was I in a Coach or on foot?</hi> On foot, anſwer'd he. <hi>Was there any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with me?</hi> I cannot remember that, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli'd he. But ſome in the <hi>Court</hi> ſaid, <hi>'Twas probable I was alone.</hi> Whereupon I then anſwer'd, That <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> was the firſt, I believed, that ever ſaw me in <hi>Lincolns-Inn-fields</hi> alone, and on foot. <hi>You ſaw, Mr. Oates, (continu'd I) Letters from me in</hi> Spain? Yes, anſwer'd he. <hi>Do not you ſay,</hi> Mr. Oates, <hi>(reply'd I) that you did not know me at</hi> Fenwick<hi>'s Chamber?</hi> I did not know you (anſwer'd he) at <hi>Wild-houſe,</hi> which was the firſt place I met you at. But he came to know you,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97478:26"/>(ſaid the <hi>Ch. Justice</hi>) by <hi>Langworth</hi>'s means in <hi>Lincolns-Inne-fields,</hi> and ſo you went together to <hi>Fenwick</hi>'s. <hi>Did you,</hi> Mr. Oates (ſaid I) <hi>ever ſee me, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with me after?</hi> Not to <hi>my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,</hi> (anſwer'd he.) <hi>Did you ever ſee me, ſaid I, at</hi> Liege? No, anſwer'd he; I came thither over night, (with one that was to take <hi>Orders</hi>) and return'd next morning. <hi>Did you ſee me in any other place beyond Sea, ſaid I again?</hi> No, repli'd he. <hi>Mr. Oates,</hi> (ſaid I) you lay to my charge here, the ſaying in <hi>Mr. Fenwicks</hi> Chamber, <hi>that I ſhould now be reveng'd;</hi> did not you in purſuance of this Story before the <hi>King</hi> accuſe me, <hi>that you had ſeen a Divorce ſued out by me at</hi> Rome? I will (anſwer'd he) give Evidence about that, when <hi>your Lordſhip</hi> is indicted of <hi>Priesthood.</hi> But I preſſing him again, and the <hi>Court</hi> telling him, that he muſt anſwer my <hi>Queſtions; Mr. Attorney</hi> with great earneſtneſs ſaid, <hi>That it was foreign, and ſpoken in another place; and that I propos'd it only to entrap and catch</hi> Mr. Oates. <hi>Catch him,</hi> repli'd I? <hi>I confeſs it, and that all my Queſtions are for that intent; but how can any thing be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97478:26"/>foreign, that proves him a Lyar and an ill man? and how can one be catch'd that ſpeaks Truth, being alſo ſure of a favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearing in his explanation, and the King's Council to back it? Therefore,</hi> Mr. Oates, <hi>(continu'd I) did you tell the King or no, that you ſaw it?</hi> I ſaid, (anſwer'd he) that it was the <hi>Report</hi> among the <hi>Fathers;</hi> and it was alſo part of the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> at <hi>Wild-houſe;</hi> for there I heard my <hi>Lord Caſtlemain</hi> ſay, <hi>that he had been at great Charges about the Divorce.</hi> But did not you (repli'd I) tell the <hi>King, you ſaw the Divorce in</hi> Mr. Strange <hi>his hands, and that he ſhow'd it you?</hi> I told the <hi>King,</hi> (anſwer'd he) that I ſaw an Account of the <hi>Divorce</hi> in <hi>Strange</hi> his hand. Here <hi>Sir Geo. Jeoffries</hi> alſo began to find fault with my <hi>Queſtions</hi> as foreign; and <hi>Mr. Attorney</hi> ſaid, that, if ſuch <hi>fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Queſtions</hi> might be ask'd, no body could defend himſelf. 'Tis not, <hi>Mr. Attorney,</hi> (anſwer'd the <hi>Ch. Juſtice</hi>) ſo very remote, if my <hi>Lord</hi> would come to application. <hi>Mr. Attorney</hi> repli'd, That any man might be catch'd at that rate; that what he ſpoke was for methods ſake, and to avoid excurſions. <hi>My Lords,</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:97478:27"/>(ſaid I) <hi>I deſire I may go on with what I have to ſay; no man can be catch'd that ſpeaks truth; nor will</hi> Mr. Attorney <hi>give me leave to catch</hi> Mr. Oates. He anſwer'd, That I had liberty in whatever belong'd to the <hi>Evidence.</hi> I come to ſhow (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli'd I) the fitneſs of my <hi>Queſtion</hi> in this Affair; for <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> having accus'd me of being at <hi>Wild-houſe,</hi> of <hi>meeting him in</hi> Lincolns-Inn fields, of aſſenting to the <hi>King's Death, becauſe I would be reveng'd;</hi> therefore ſince he has brought the <hi>King</hi> upon the Stage, I'le now refreſh his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, by telling him what he accus'd me of before his <hi>Majeſty.</hi> as alſo before your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> in this <hi>Court; therefore,</hi> Mr. Oates, <hi>did you ſay you ſaw a Divorce or no?</hi> I do not remember, (anſwer'd he) that I ſaid ſo; but I remember you ſaid, you had been at great Expence about one. I hope now <hi>(my Lord)</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli'd <hi>Mr. Attorney</hi>) he has given you a ſatisfactory <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 'Tis very well at preſent, (anſwer'd I) and ſo we ended for that time.</p>
               <p>This is the ſum of his <hi>Charge,</hi> and all the material <hi>Queſtions</hi> and <hi>Anſwers</hi> to it; but as he was going out of <hi>Court,</hi> I
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97478:27"/>deſir'd he might not ſtir, till the end of the Tryal, unleſs it were a general Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge allow'd to <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing determin'd in the Affirmative, I reſted ſatisfied, and then <hi>Mr. Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> took his place.</p>
               <p>Now before he was ſworn, I told the <hi>Judges,</hi> that he could not, I conceiv'd, be a Witneſs, and therefore pray'd he might be laid aſide. The <hi>Ch. Justice</hi> ask'd, Why? Becauſe (anſwer'd I) he has committed ſo many enormous Crimes, and thoſe upon <hi>Record,</hi> that by Law he cannot be heard in any Court of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. What <hi>Records</hi> (repli'd the <hi>Ch. Justice</hi>) have you? There are <hi>fourteen</hi> (anſwer'd I) already found; but not to be too troubleſome to your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> I only offer you <hi>ſix;</hi> which prove how he has been <hi>pillor'd, burnt in the hand,</hi> and even <hi>outlaw'd for Felony;</hi> whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my <hi>Sollicitor</hi> (being call'd) deliver'd them to the <hi>Clerk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 1ſt. <hi>Record</hi> ſhow'd, <hi>That having,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>25 Car.</hi> 2.</note> Anno 73. <hi>ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from one</hi> Mr. Blagrave, <hi>a Cabinet worth</hi> 10 l. <hi>and</hi> 10 <hi>pieces of Gold in it, he was convicted of the Fact, and burnt in the hand at the</hi> Old-Baily.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:97478:28"/>
               <p>The 2d. prov'd, <hi>That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">27 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.</note> Anno 75. <hi>at</hi> Chelmſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-Aſſizes, (<hi>held before</hi> Sir Thomas Twiſden) <hi>indicted, for ſtealing from one</hi> Tatterſon 4 l. 10 s. <hi>he broke Priſon before he could be tryed, and was thereupon out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 3d. 4th. and 5th. ſhow'd, <hi>That at the</hi> Aſſizes,
<note n="*" place="margin">29 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>Aug.</hi> 4.</note> Anno 77. (<hi>held for the</hi> County of Wilts) <hi>he had three ſeveral Indictments brought against him for venting falſe Guinneys, and that being upon each convicted before</hi> Sir Thomas Jones, <hi>he was condemn'd to ſtand with a Paper on his Forehead three ſeveral days in the</hi> Pillory, <hi>and that twice (as Witneſſes in Court would prove) he ſtood at</hi> Salisbury, <hi>but broke (before the</hi> 3d. <hi>time) Priſon, and got away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 6th. <hi>was a Conviction at the</hi> Old-Baily,
<note n="*" place="margin">30 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>May</hi> 16.</note> Anno 78. <hi>of his again venting falſe Guinneys, for which (beſides Impriſonment) he was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> 50 l. Sir Tho. Jones <hi>being then alſo one of the Judges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe were the Heads of the <hi>Records;</hi> but it being now a <hi>Point in Law,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Dangerfield</hi> could be heard as a
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97478:28"/>
                  <hi>Witneſs,</hi> I demanded <hi>Councel</hi> to argue it; and had <hi>Mr. Jones, Mr. Sanders,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Darnel,</hi> aſſign'd me. <hi>Mr. Jones</hi> ſaid he was not prepar'd; <hi>Mr. Sanders</hi> happen'd not to be in <hi>Court;</hi> ſo that <hi>Mr. Darnel</hi> addreſſing himſelf to the <hi>Judges,</hi> very learnedly ſpake to this effect:</p>
               <p>I conceive (with ſubmiſſion to your <hi>Lordſhips</hi>) that notwithſtanding this <hi>Pardon, Dangerfield</hi> cannot be a <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Pardon</hi> hath only taken away the <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> and not the <hi>Guilt</hi> of his Offence. <hi>My Lords,</hi> It is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judg'd in
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fol.</hi> 41.</note> 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. That a man attainted of Felony, (as <hi>Dangerfield</hi> is) tho' he be afterwards pardon'd, cannot be ſworn of a <hi>Jury.</hi> Of the ſame opinion alſo was the Court of <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> in 9 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> as we find it in <hi>Brownlow</hi>'s and <hi>Goldsbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough</hi>'s
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fol.</hi> 34.</note> Reports; and my <hi>Lord Cook</hi> in <hi>Brown</hi>'s and <hi>Craſhaw</hi>'s Caſe, (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by <hi>Mr. Bulstrode</hi>) was of the ſame
<note n="*" place="margin">2d. <hi>Rep. fol.</hi> 154.</note> opinion; <hi>viz.</hi> That a man attainted, tho' pardon'd, can never ſerve upon an Inqueſt, and conſequently cannot be a Witneſs in any
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97478:29"/>Caſe; and the Reaſon he gave was, becauſe he is not <hi>Probus &amp; legalis homo;</hi> for, (ſays he) <hi>Poena mori potest, culpa perennis erit.</hi> In <hi>Mr. Brown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi>'s
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fol.</hi> 47.</note> 2d. <hi>Report,</hi> 'tis adjudg'd, That if the <hi>King</hi> pardons a man attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for giving a falſe Verdict, yet he ſhall not be at another time impanell'd upon any <hi>Jury;</hi> for tho' the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> be pardon'd, the <hi>Guilt</hi> remains: Upon which Authorities I humbly ſubmit to your Judgments, whether <hi>Dangerfield</hi> can be a Witneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr. Attorney</hi> on the contrary urg'd, That the <hi>King's Pardon</hi> had not only ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away the <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> but the <hi>Guilt</hi> alſo, and ſo clears the Perſon from the Crime and Infamy; and for this, he cited the Caſe in <hi>Fitz-Herbert Coron,</hi> where, in an <hi>Appeal of Felony,</hi> the <hi>Defendant</hi> offer'd <hi>Tryal by Battel,</hi> and the <hi>Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff</hi> counterpleaded it by ſaying, The <hi>Defendant</hi> being apprehended, eſcap'd and brake <hi>Priſon,</hi> which preſumes a guiltineſs; but (proceeds he) if the <hi>King</hi> pardons that <hi>breaking of Priſon,</hi> the <hi>Deſendant</hi> ſhall be reſtored to the <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel,</hi> and the <hi>Counterplea</hi> taken away,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97478:29"/>
                  <hi>Mr. Sollicitor</hi> argu'd to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; That the <hi>King's Pardon</hi> doth not only clear the <hi>Offence</hi> it ſelf, but all the <hi>Dependencies, Penalties,</hi> and <hi>Diſabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> incident to it. <hi>Mr. Sergeant Jeoffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> cited <hi>Cuddington</hi>'s <hi>Caſe,</hi> in my Lord <hi>Hobart</hi>'s <hi>Reports,</hi> That the <hi>Pardon</hi> takes away the <hi>Reatum</hi> as well as the <hi>Poenam;</hi> and he ſaid beſides, That the conſtant <hi>Practice</hi> at the <hi>Old-Baily</hi> had been, to admit an <hi>attainted Felon</hi> after his <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> to be a <hi>Witneſs;</hi> and this <hi>Sir Francis Withens</hi> did alſo much inſiſt upon. The Court anſwer'd as to the <hi>Practice,</hi> That perhaps no Exception had been made to it by the Parties concern'd; but doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little <hi>Mr. Darnel</hi>'s Citations, they call'd for the Books, and finding them true, ſent <hi>Mr. Justice Raimond</hi> to the <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> for their Opinion, which was, <hi>That a man attainted (as</hi> Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field) <hi>upon an Outlawry for Felony, could not be a Witneſs, tho' pardon'd; but if at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted, and burnt in the hand, he might.</hi> Now this being thought the preſent <hi>Caſe,</hi> tho' ſince upon further conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it is found to have been a miſtake; for <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was not <hi>burnt in the hand</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:97478:30"/>for the <hi>Felony</hi> upon which he was <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law'd,</hi> but lately pardon'd; ſo that by reaſon of that <hi>Attainder,</hi> he can never be again a <hi>legal Witneſs.</hi> I ſay, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thought the preſent <hi>Caſe,</hi> the <hi>Court</hi> told me, as they did before, that tho' he were to be heard, yet any <hi>Record</hi> to invalidate his Teſtimony, and ſhow what a man he was, ſhould be read and conſider'd; and thereupon he was <hi>ſworn,</hi> the <hi>Diſpute</hi> having laſted above an hour.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Evidence</hi> was this;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dangerfield</hi>'s Evidence.</note> That being ſent to me with a <hi>Letter</hi> from my <hi>Lady Powis,</hi> which he gave me, I diſpatch'd him back with an <hi>Anſwer,</hi> which her <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> open'd and read aloud in his preſence, <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> being alſo by: That the ſaid <hi>Anſwer</hi> expreſs'd a liking of him the ſaid <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield,</hi> as a fit man to inſtruct the <hi>Youths,</hi> who were ſent from <hi>St. Omers</hi> againſt <hi>Mr. Oates: That I did teach thoſe Youths what to ſay at the Tryals:</hi> That when any <hi>One</hi> was out of his <hi>Part,</hi> it was common for to ſay, <hi>I must go to my</hi> Lord Caſtlemain; and being ask'd by the <hi>Ch. Justice,</hi> Who ſaid ſo? He anſwer'd,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97478:30"/>That among others, he heard <hi>Gifford</hi> ſay it: That I order'd the taking <hi>Lane</hi> out of <hi>Priſon:</hi> That I approv'd of the <hi>Letters</hi> and <hi>List of Names,</hi> which he brought me from <hi>Mr. Nevil,</hi> alias <hi>Pain,</hi> to be convey'd into the Houſes of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> being all to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with thoſe he had already put into <hi>Col. Manſel</hi>'s Chamber, tending to the credit of the <hi>Sham-Plot:</hi> That to this end I order'd him to imploy men to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the ſaid <hi>Letters:</hi> That I being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by a <hi>Letter</hi> from him, that the Perſons imploy'd had finiſh'd their Work, I ſent him by a <hi>Meſſenger</hi> (that is now in <hi>Court</hi>) 40 <hi>s.</hi> having ſent as much more to <hi>Mrs. Cellier,</hi> as ſhe told him: That in the middle of <hi>August,</hi> 79. he <hi>(Dangerfield)</hi> came to me, (and one of my Servants that was by, being ſent away) I ſaid to him, (with a very auſtere countenance, and like one that meditated Revenge) <hi>Why did you refuſe to perform what the Lords in the Tower pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to you?</hi> He ask'd, <hi>If it were to kill the King?</hi> And I anſwer'd, Yes; but ſeeing me in fury, he ran down ſtairs, and never came to me more: That (as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97478:31"/>he thinks) I was then writing the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium;</hi> for he ſaw ſome words in a <hi>Paragraph,</hi> which he after wards ſaw in the <hi>printed Book,</hi> and I had alſo then a Pen in my hand and Ink by: That I us'd to call the <hi>King</hi> TYRANT; and being ask'd how and upon what occaſion I ſaid ſo; He anſwer'd, That if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of me (for example) when <hi>his Majesty</hi> return'd from <hi>Windſor?</hi> I would ſay, When the <hi>Tyrant</hi> pleaſes; and he heard me uſe the word to <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> in <hi>Powis-houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the chief <hi>Question</hi> which I ask'd him was; Whether I were not angry for his going to the <hi>Tower</hi> to my <hi>Lord Powis</hi> and the reſt in my Name, about printing the <hi>Jeſuits Speeches,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forbade <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> from ever ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him any more to my <hi>Houſe;</hi> telling her withal, <hi>If he came, I would order my Servants to kick him?</hi> This he abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deni'd; and then I ſaid, I ſhould now (with the <hi>Courts</hi> Permiſſion) produce <hi>Evidence</hi> to diſprove what had been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd againſt me, and that I would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with <hi>Mr. Oates;</hi> tho' I could not but rejoyce, that <hi>Mr. Dangerfield</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97478:31"/>as a <hi>Witneſs,</hi> ſince every word that he had mention'd to them ſhould be proved a notorious <hi>Lye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 1ſt thing I offer'd,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> and the <hi>Haſtings</hi> Record.</note> was, (after the calling for <hi>Mr. Parker</hi>) a <hi>Record</hi> from <hi>Haſtings,</hi> which ſhow'd, <hi>that</hi> Mr. Oates <hi>had</hi> (Anno 1675.) <hi>accus'd this</hi> Parker <hi>of Sodomy, and that He having been try'd for it, was by the Jury brought in Not Guilty.</hi> The <hi>Ch. Juſtice</hi> ask'd me, What I meant by this; for it follow'd not (he ſaid) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Jury,</hi> did not find a Charge, that therefore the <hi>Accuſer</hi> was to be deem'd forſworn? I do not (my <hi>Lord</hi>) (repli'd I) ſay he muſt; but I urge this <hi>Record,</hi> to prove that he did accuſe one whom the <hi>Jury</hi> found innocent; and then I ſhall ſhow by <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> the Motives that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd the <hi>Jury</hi> to their <hi>Verdict;</hi> to wit, The known antecedent Malice of <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> againſt <hi>Mr. Parker,</hi> and the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Teſtimony of <hi>Neighbours</hi> againſt him; for ſome averr'd, <hi>That they being then in, or near the Place where the Fact was ſaid to be committed, ſaw not</hi> Mr. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker <hi>there;</hi> and others, <hi>That</hi> Mr. Parker <hi>was with them all that Afternoon at a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97478:32"/>merry Meeting. Mr. Juſtice Dolbin</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, That <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> ſtood not there to anſwer all pretended faults; and the <hi>Ch. Juſtice</hi> ask'd, That ſuppoſing it true, that <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> proſecuted a man for <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony,</hi> and the <hi>Jury</hi> acquitted him, what uſe could I make of it? For, according to my Doctrine, (there being in moſt Caſes Witneſſes on both ſides) the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants</hi> Evidence muſt be perjur'd when it goes for the <hi>Plaintiff,</hi> and the <hi>Plaintiffs</hi> when it goes for the <hi>Defendant. My Lord,</hi> (anſwer'd I) this is my Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, <hi>Parker</hi> is innocent, and <hi>Oates</hi> is his poſitive Accuſer, of a capital Crime, when he the ſaid <hi>Parker</hi> was in another place, which ſhows his malicious Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Practice. The <hi>Ch. Juſtice</hi> repli'd, That no body knew the Motives of the Jury but themſelves; and that the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs amounted to nothing. Here is alſo, (ſaid I) an <hi>Order of Council,</hi> which ſhows how malicious and deſign'd <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> his Accuſation was; for whilſt this young <hi>Parker</hi> was in Priſon, expecting his <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> (to take all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and aſſiſtance from him) accuſes his <hi>Father,</hi> (who was a <hi>Juſtice of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97478:32"/>Peace,</hi> and a conſiderable man in the Town) of ſcandalous words againſt the <hi>Lords of the Privy Council,</hi> and ſo ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him by a <hi>Meſſenger,</hi> he remain'd in Cuſtody, till the <hi>King</hi> (upon the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the whole Matter at the <hi>Board</hi>) declar'd him wrong'd; and then diſmiſſing him, ſent away <hi>Oates</hi> with the greateſt Contempt imaginable. Was this, ſays the <hi>Ch. Juſtice,</hi> before the <hi>Plot?</hi> Yes, <hi>my Lord,</hi> anſwer'd I. 'Tis of no moment, repli'd he. It plainly ſhows (ſays I) what kind of man <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> was, and therefore I refer it to the <hi>Jury's</hi> Conſideration. The <hi>Jury</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, <hi>(Sir Geo. Jeoffries)</hi> muſt not take notice of it; for it ſignifies nothing; and thereupon <hi>Parker</hi> (who came to ſhow all the Particulars of that Matter) withdrew, without being heard. What has your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> more to ſay (conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues the <hi>Ch. Juſtice?</hi>) Having thus, <hi>(My Lord)</hi> (ſaid I) ſhow'd you ſome of <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> his Actions whilſt he was a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> I will now acquaint you with others after his becoming a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> and firſt I will bring you one who made him of that <hi>Religion,</hi> and whom Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:97478:33"/>has ſince re-converted to be a <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> Why then (anſwer'd the <hi>Ch. Juſtice</hi>) there's a <hi>Rowland</hi> for your <hi>Oliver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr.
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Berry.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Berry,</hi> alias <hi>Hutchinſon,</hi> (who was the man) appear'd at Call; and I, to ſhow the ſaid <hi>Berry</hi>'s familiarity and great acquaintance with Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> demanded, If he had not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <hi>reconcil'd</hi> him, and made him a <hi>Papist?</hi> He anſwering, <hi>Yes;</hi> the <hi>Ch. Juſtice</hi> ſaid, I ought not to ask ſuch Queſtions as might endanger his life; and preſently the <hi>King's Council</hi> charg'd him with <hi>Treaſon?</hi> I repli'd, That he had been a <hi>Popiſh Priest,</hi> but was now converted, and had publickly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd his Errors. At laſt, after a great deal of do, he was commanded to tell what he knew of Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and then he ſpoke thus:</p>
               <p>That at his coming out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, about <hi>April</hi> 77. he found Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ready to go to <hi>Valadolid,</hi> where he went to ſtudy his <hi>Philoſophy</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity:</hi> That he receiv'd from thence <hi>Letters</hi> from him: That in the <hi>Winter</hi> following, (when he came to <hi>London</hi> again) he underſtood Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> was
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97478:33"/>return'd, and gone to be a <hi>Scholar</hi> at St. <hi>Omers:</hi> That in the <hi>Summer</hi> after, he met with Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> in Town, who told him, That he had left the <hi>Colledge, and that he would ſuffer no more for Conſcience, it being a hard thing to want Pread:</hi> That finding Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> in ſo poor a condition, he the ſaid Mr. <hi>Berry,</hi> imploy'd him to write ſeveral by-things for him, and gave him 10 <hi>s.</hi> for his pains: That Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> did much complain of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not regard him; and ſaid, <hi>That they had offer'd him a Futler's place:</hi> That after the <hi>Diſcovery</hi> made by Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> he the ſaid Mr. <hi>Berry</hi> went and queſtion'd him very much about the things he had accus'd the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> of, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he heard, that the <hi>Scholars</hi> of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> (who were at leaſt <hi>ſixſcore</hi> in number) and not only vertuous perſons, as he (Mr. <hi>Berry</hi>) well knew, but often commended as ſuch by Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) could witneſs his being at the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> with them, when he pretended his being here in Town; to which Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> anſwer'd, <hi>That he valu'd not what they could ſay, for they were all outlaw'd perſons;</hi> and further Mr. <hi>Berry</hi> ſaid, that Mr.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97478:34"/>
                  <hi>Oates</hi> was very kind to him, and gave him 20 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Berry</hi> having given this <hi>Evidence,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> denying all that pung'd, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Berry</hi> began to exhort him to <hi>ſpeak Truth, and to remember there was a God in Heaven,</hi> with more to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but the <hi>King's Council</hi> inſtead of applauding his <hi>Serinon,</hi> laid again <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to his charge, <hi>as having perſwaded a Subject to the Popiſh Religion, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Pardon.</hi> They preſs'd therefore to have his <hi>Confeſſion</hi> recorded, and him conſequently ſecur'd. Then one of them turning to me, ſaid, (in a tone audible enough at leaſt to thoſe at, or about the Bar) That by abounding in my own ſence, I had brought my <hi>Witneſs</hi> to the <hi>Gallows;</hi> and ask'd alſo my Councel, if he had methodiz'd that excellent Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence? I repeated to him, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Berry<hi>'s Converſion to the</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion had wip'd away all faults of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> nor knew I what to ſay more, but to tell him, if he had a mind to hang his <hi>Converts,</hi> he might. Now whilſt the <hi>Court</hi> and the <hi>King's Council</hi> were argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Mr. <hi>Berry</hi> ſlipt away, which being
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97478:34"/>at laſt perceiv'd, they commanded him to be recall'd; and then the <hi>Ch. Justice</hi> asked him, <hi>What Religion he was of?</hi> He anſwer'd, <hi>A Protestant.</hi> The <hi>King's Council</hi> notwithſtanding inſiſted ſtill to have his foreſaid <hi>Confeſſion</hi> recorded, which made the <hi>Ch. Juſtice</hi> at laſt declare, that it ſhould be done, in caſe any body made <hi>Oath</hi> of it; But, ſeveral being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and refuſing to do it, a grave and <hi>Reverend</hi> Divine, (who was <hi>Dean of Rippon,</hi> as I was told) roſe up and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the <hi>Court,</hi> that this Mr. <hi>Berry</hi> was his <hi>Curate at</hi> Barking; that the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> London, having heard ſomething againſt his Preaching, had ſent him (the ſaid <hi>Doctor</hi>) word, that he would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide him another; and that laſt <hi>Saturday</hi> at Dinner his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> told him, he was diſtracted. Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> preſently acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd, that he had known, and look'd upon him to be ſuch a one; and ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out more words he was diſmiſs'd.</p>
               <p>Then I called for one Mr.
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Armſtrong.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Armſtrong,</hi> and ask'd him, If he had not been Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s School-fellow at <hi>Valladolid?</hi> He anſwer'd, Yes; and ſo I deſir'd him to tell the <hi>Court</hi> in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97478:35"/>what condition Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> lived there. He ſaid, That he himſelf came not to <hi>Valladolid</hi> till about <hi>Sept.</hi> 77. Mr. <hi>Oatei</hi> having been there ſome three months before him: That Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> was only a <hi>Scholar</hi> like himſelf and others, ſitting at the ſame <hi>Table,</hi> and going to the ſame <hi>School</hi> with them, till his departure. Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> anſwer'd, That he was ready to <hi>Commence,</hi> when <hi>Armſtrong</hi> and other <hi>Youths</hi> came, who being but <hi>Strangers,</hi> and not underſtanding their <hi>Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Dictates, the Fathers deſir'd him,</hi> (Oates) <hi>to teach them, and to ſhow them the way to School, which he twice or thrice did. Armſtrong</hi> repli'd, That it was not ſo, and that <hi>Oates</hi> was but a <hi>Scholar</hi> himſelf as the reſt were.</p>
               <p>After this I called for Mr.
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Palmer,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Dorrington.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Dorrington</hi> and Mr. <hi>Palmer;</hi> Mr. <hi>Palmer</hi> firſt appearing, I entreated him to give an account of Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s condition at St. <hi>Omers;</hi> who ſaid, That <hi>Oates</hi> was but a <hi>Scholar</hi> there whilſt he ſtay'd; that he ſtill went to <hi>School,</hi> and play'd with the reſt of the <hi>School-boys;</hi> but being an ancient man, he had more freedom than the reſt, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97478:35"/>ſo ſate at a <hi>by-Table</hi> in the <hi>Refectory,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Scholars.</hi> Mr. <hi>Dorrington</hi> could not for the Crowd preſently get into <hi>Court;</hi> but way being at laſt made, I ask'd him the ſame thing, which he affirm'd, and ſo retir'd.</p>
               <p>The next Call was for Mr.
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Grigſon,</hi> and <hi>Rigby.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Grigſon</hi> and <hi>Ellen Rigby; Grigſon</hi> coming in, I ask'd him, if Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> were not his <hi>Lodger?</hi> He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, <hi>Yes,</hi> at <hi>Easter,</hi> 77. as alſo after; and in ſhort declar'd, that he was in a poor condition during his ſtay with him. Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ask'd <hi>Grigſon,</hi> if Mr. <hi>Fenwick</hi> had never paid for him? He ſaid, Yes, after he came from St. <hi>Omers.</hi> As for <hi>Ellen Rigby,</hi> I ſaid, ſhe was ready to teſtifie, (as ſhe had done in Sir <hi>Geo. Wakeman</hi>'s <hi>Tryal</hi>) That Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> us'd (in the year 78.) to beg of Mr. <hi>Pickering</hi> in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> and that at laſt ſhe had Orders (as being a Servant there) not to let him come in any more. The <hi>Court</hi> intimated, that they had heard this of her formerly, and therefore I told her ſhe might retire, as ſhe did, without ſpeaking. Beſides Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> deni'd not his poor condition, but confeſt, <hi>he had nothing to live upon
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97478:36"/>but what he was allow'd by the Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> Whereupon the <hi>Court</hi> ſaid, <hi>that it ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d they allow'd him but very meanly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Witneſſes</hi> being gone, I ask'd Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> whether he did not ſay, he came over with Mr. <hi>Hildeſley</hi> to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult</hi> in <hi>April</hi> 1678? He anſwer'd, <hi>Yes;</hi> and then Mr.
<note place="margin">Mr <hi>Hildeſley.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hildeſley</hi> was call'd, who abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni'd his coming over with him. The <hi>Court</hi> ſaid, That this buſineſs had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy been before them, and that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> his being then in Town was proved by others. I do not (repli'd I) come now to meddle with that buſineſs, neither ſhall I bring any old thing before the <hi>Court,</hi> without ſome new proof or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; and thereupon I called one Mr. <hi>Osborn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Osborn.</hi>
                  </note> who declar'd to this purpoſe; That in <hi>April</hi> 78. he met Mr. <hi>Hildeſley</hi> newly come from St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and diſcourſing with him about their former <hi>School-fellows,</hi> and what new ones were then there, Mr. <hi>Hildeſley</hi> ſaid, He had left there among others a <hi>Minister</hi> at School called <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Lucy,</hi> his true Name being <hi>Oates;</hi> but that he demean'd himſelf ſo ill, that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97478:36"/>he believ'd he would be ſent away as ſoon as the <hi>Provincial</hi> came. To ſhow alſo that this was no invention of Mr. <hi>Osborn,</hi> I told the <hi>Court</hi> I had ſome <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> of quality ready (one of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Protestant</hi>) to witneſs, that Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi> had told them this very Story at that time, to wit in <hi>Apr.</hi> 78.
<note place="margin">Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
                  <hi>For the</hi> Reader <hi>must know, that theſe collateral Witneſſes talking (it ſeems) about a Gentlewoman in Barkſhire, Mr. Osborn (their near Relation being by) acquainted them, that he had that day met with a Kinſman of hers, to wit, his old School-fellow</hi> Hildeſley, <hi>who was new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come from St.</hi> Omers, <hi>and ſo told them the Diſcourſe they had had together; which paſſage being remembred by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Lady, after Mr.</hi> Oates<hi>'s Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, made her much more queſtion the truth of his Information, when once ſhe found that he pretended to come over with the ſaid</hi> Hildeſley.</p>
               <p>I inſiſted much upon this <hi>Evidence,</hi> as a Confirmation of <hi>Hildeſley</hi>'s Teſtimony, and conſequently that <hi>Oates</hi> came not over with him, as he ſwears; and Mr. <hi>Juſtice Jones</hi> was pleas'd to repeat my
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97478:37"/>Inference; but the <hi>Ch. Juſtice</hi> (upon my offering the collateral Witneſſes) told me, that it was needleſs to call them, except I could bring ſome that came over with <hi>Fildeſley;</hi> the thing other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe being ſtill a <hi>Hear-ſay;</hi> yet the <hi>Jury</hi> might, if they pleas'd, conſider it. Mr. <hi>Juſtice Dolben</hi> alſo thought it but a <hi>Hear-ſay,</hi> and that therefore it brought with it no new force or value.</p>
               <p>This buſineſs being thus over I call'd for Mr. <hi>Lytcott,</hi> another of my Witneſſes, to prove, <hi>that I had never offer'd at a Divorce,</hi> and conſequently that even Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s preſent Teſtimony, of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, <hi>that I had ſpent much money about one,</hi> was a lye. Having therefore deſir'd him to ſpeak, he ſaid, <hi>That it was morally impoſſible there ſhould be a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce, becauſe (he knew) there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuch a Deſign.</hi> The <hi>Court</hi> not liking the Iſſue, ſeem'd from the beginning to diſcourage it, which I deſir'd, they would not do; but Sir <hi>George Geoffries,</hi> to diſcountenance it further, would have it, that all that my <hi>Witneſs</hi> had to ſay was, <hi>That he never knew of any;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Juſtice Dolben</hi> was pleas'd to think
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97478:37"/>the Evidence could be of no moment. But I urg'd, that it would certainly be material; for if he proved, (as I knew both he and others could) that I never endeavour'd at a <hi>Divorce,</hi> then it was falſe that I ſpent money about one. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> (as ſhould be prov'd, if their Lordſhips had forgotten it) had accus'd me, even in that very <hi>Court</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> as alſo before the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> and before the <hi>Houſe of Commons, That he ſaw the Divorce which I ſued for;</hi> Therefore having ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver offer'd at it—The <hi>Court</hi> (inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting me here) asked, What then? and that I muſt not go to prove what was not pertinent to the Queſtion; or what was ſaid in another place, tho' falſe. But I inſiſting, that he had now at this very Tryal charg'd me with ſaying, <hi>That I had ſpent much money about the Divorce,</hi> whenas I had never aim'd at it; my <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice</hi> ſaid, He would acquaint me with the uſual proceedings of a <hi>Court</hi> in this nature; <hi>viz.</hi> That if I ſhould come to prove a Falſhood ſworn by Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> in another place, they were not to take notice of it, ſince I muſt have firſt prov'd
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:97478:38"/>him perjur'd, which was not their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs now to try; for if what I preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to were granted, I might make what <hi>Witneſs</hi> I pleas'd a <hi>Lyar,</hi> becauſe being unprepar'd he could not defend himſelf; But if Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſwore in another place, contrary to what he here aſſerts, it would be a very proper and fit thing to ſhow. Now (continu'd he) Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> only ſwears, <hi>he does not remember he had ſeen the Divorce,</hi> but remembers you ſaid, <hi>You had ſpent much money about one,</hi> which comes only to an <hi>Hear-ſay</hi> from your Lordſhip. I anſwer'd as I had done before, That I never ſo much as offer'd at one, and therefore could not ſpend money about it: That his ſeeing of it, was his conſtant charge, and that if he ly'd in one thing, he might do ſo in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I further ſaid, That I would have indicted him for <hi>Perjury</hi> long ago, if I might; for to that end I had ſent to the <hi>Clerk of the Peace,</hi> for Copies of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Langhorn,</hi> according to my <hi>Councel</hi>'s Directions, but that he would not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them without Mr. <hi>Attorney</hi>'s War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, who refus'd one, tho' often ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97478:38"/>as thoſe that waited upon him could atteſt. I bade them (anſwer'd <hi>Mr. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney</hi>) firſt petition the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> for an <hi>Order,</hi> and when they did ſo, it was not granted them. I know (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli'd I) that the <hi>Council</hi> would not; but yet I did all I could in the Affair. The <hi>Court</hi> ſtill deeming Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Teſtimony of my ſaying, <hi>I had ſpent much money about a Divorce,</hi> no contradiction; and his former averring, <hi>that he ſaw one;</hi> a foreign thing. I urg'd again, That he had averr'd it in that very <hi>Court</hi> before their <hi>Lordſhips;</hi> which they all aſſur'd me, they did not remember. Finding it therefore ungrateful to bring this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to a further examination, I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the whole to them, tho' I offer'd to prove, what they had forgotten, and ſo I bade Mr. <hi>Lytcott</hi> withdraw.</p>
               <p>Then the <hi>Court</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>Records</hi> (already mentioned againſt <hi>Dangerfield</hi>) to be read; which being done,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Duddel,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Ceiliere.</hi>
                  </note> I call'd for one Mr. <hi>Duddel,</hi> (who had been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly a <hi>Witneſs</hi> ſubpoena'd againſt Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> by <hi>Dangerfield</hi>) as alſo for Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> her ſelf. At her appearing ſome
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97478:39"/>of the Auditory began to <hi>hiſs;</hi> but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my entreating the <hi>Judges</hi> to forbid that <hi>Bear-Garden</hi> proceeding, there was a ſtop put to it, nor was there the leaſt offer at any other rudeneſs during the whole <hi>Tryal.</hi> I ask'd then Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> Whether I had not chidden her at <hi>Dangerfield</hi>'s, going to the <hi>Tower</hi> in my Name to the <hi>Earl of Powis</hi> and the reſt, about printing the <hi>Jeſuits Speeches;</hi> and whether I did not tell her, <hi>If ever Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield came more to my Houſe, I would make my Servant kick him?</hi> She acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd all to be true, affirming, that it happen'd on that very
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>June</hi> 23.29.</note> day twelve-month; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſhe proteſted, ſhe would have ſent him after to me with a <hi>Letter,</hi> but that he refus'd it, ſaying, he would rather go a hundred miles than come near me. But <hi>Dangerfield</hi> denying all, Mr. <hi>Dud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> poſitively witneſſed, <hi>That the ſaid</hi> Dangerfield <hi>had (about a week after the Execution of the five Jeſuits) expreſs'd to him the great trouble he was in at my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for his going to the Tower as aforeſaid.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">My Lady <hi>Powis.</hi>
                  </note> I deſir'd alſo that my <hi>Lady Powis</hi> (who then
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97478:39"/>happen'd to be in <hi>Court</hi>) might be ask'd, Whether ſhe had written to me by <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield,</hi> as he had ſworn? Which being done, her <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> (ſtanding in her place) ſolemnly declar'd, <hi>She never ſent Letter to me, or any body elſe by</hi> Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field; <hi>that ſhe receiv'd none from me, nor from any body elſe by him; nor ever read one to any body in his preſence. Mrs. Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liere</hi> being call'd back, declar'd alſo, that ſhe never knew or heard of any thus brought from me. And then I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the <hi>Judges,</hi> that I would now diſprove <hi>the Lye, of my teaching the St.</hi> Omers <hi>Scholars their Leſſon, as</hi> Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field <hi>ſaid I had done;</hi> but the <hi>King's Council</hi> hinder'd me, by calling of <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Witneſſes</hi> to confirm my <hi>Adverſaries</hi> Teſtimony; and theſe were <hi>Sir Richard Barker, Mr. Lawſon, Mr. Turner, and one Woodman,</hi> who all teſtifi'd as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows:</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Richard Barker</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,
<note place="margin">Sir <hi>R. Barker.</hi>
                  </note> and related (as he had done in the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and Mr. <hi>Langhorn</hi>'s <hi>Tryal</hi>) how his Servants acquainted him of Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s being at his Houſe before <hi>Whitſontide</hi> 78. but upon my telling the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97478:40"/>
                  <hi>Court,</hi> that I medled not now with that Matter, the <hi>Knight</hi> was diſmiſs'd; and ſo there was no need of his <hi>Maid</hi> or <hi>Boy,</hi> who were at hand, as the <hi>King's Council</hi> inform'd the <hi>Court.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Lawſon.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Mr. Lawſon</hi> was next call'd upon; and as ſoon as he appeared, <hi>Mr. Juſtice Dolben</hi> gave him great Commendations, as being a Gentleman's Son of Quality, and a very honeſt man; as alſo, that tho' he were my <hi>Solicitor,</hi> yet he would not (he was ſure) ſay an Untruth; or words to that purpoſe. But before he was ſworn, <hi>Mr. Attorney</hi> put him by, and call'd <hi>Turner,</hi> which proceeded (as we ſince found) from this; That he (the ſaid <hi>Mr. Lawſon</hi>) being ſubpoena'd by <hi>Dangerfield</hi> the night before, had decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſome of his Acquaintance, <hi>That he was ſo far from ſeeing</hi> Dangerfield <hi>at my Houſe in</hi> Auguſt 78. <hi>that he was gone out of Town long before to the North, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that Circuit.</hi> Now this Evidence (ſo diametrically oppoſite to <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi>'s <hi>Oath</hi>) would have demonſtrated his falſhood; and therefore having time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly notice of it, He, or ſome of his Gang caus'd <hi>Mr. Attorney</hi> to ſtop, as I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97478:40"/>and <hi>Turner</hi> being call'd, was ask'd,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Turner.</hi>
                  </note> When he ſaw <hi>Dangerfield</hi> laſt at my Houſe? The man appearing in as great confuſion and diſorder, as any one can be imagin'd that comes into ſo great an Aſſembly, anſwer'd, <hi>That he could not exactly tell.</hi> The <hi>Court</hi> bade him tell as near as he could. He repli'd, <hi>He believ'd in June, about Mr. Langhorn's Tryal.</hi> Might it not have been (ſaid the <hi>Chief Justice</hi>) in <hi>July?</hi> He anſwer'd, <hi>He thought it might.</hi> But why (ſaid the <hi>Ch. Justice</hi> again) might it not be in <hi>August?</hi> He (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing ſtill confus'd) anſwer'd, <hi>He could not be poſitive, but he believ'd it was in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Did you then ſee <hi>Dangerfield</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Court</hi>) with my <hi>Lord? No,</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd he) <hi>As I was coming down ſtairs, I ſaw him in a Room below waiting. Woodman</hi> being call'd,
<note place="margin">Woodman.</note> was queſtion'd about money brought from me; who ſaid, That he was ſent to my <hi>Houſe</hi> with a Letter from <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> by her <hi>Daughter</hi> (as he remembers) for <hi>money;</hi> and that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd there about 3 <hi>l.</hi> But being ask'd, Whether it were for <hi>Dangerfield?</hi> he
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97478:41"/>repli'd, <hi>He knew nothing of that, but thought it was for the Priſoners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are all the <hi>Witneſſes pro</hi> and <hi>con;</hi> and now I call'd for <hi>Mr. Lytcott</hi> again, as one of my <hi>Witneſſes</hi> to diſprove <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield's Lye</hi> about my Teaching the <hi>St. Omers Scholars;</hi> for I confeſs, that I was more concern'd at this Calumny, than at all the reſt; But when <hi>Mr. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice Dolben</hi> told me, that he would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it would be time loſt, I thought it better to wave a thing not abſolutely material, than to diſpleaſe and put the <hi>Court</hi> out of humour: Therefore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing my ſelf to the <hi>Bench,</hi> I ſaid; <hi>That I would now with their permiſſion make a Recapitulation of what had paſs'd;</hi> and ſo going to peruſe my <hi>Notes,</hi> (for I had written a great deal) the <hi>Ch. Juſtice</hi> repli'd, That I might do as I thought ſit, but that he muſt be gone. Wherefore ſeveral about me hinted, That the <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Jury</hi> were all tired, by reaſon of the exceſſive heat, (for I had been near 6 hours at the <hi>Bar,</hi> and 5 in my <hi>Tryal:</hi>) That there was but one Witneſs at moſt againſt me: That all was plain, that the <hi>Judges</hi> would fully give an account of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97478:41"/>every thing; and that more words would rather be a prejudice, than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. This had no little weight with me; and beſides it would be infinitely advantagious for me, (I knew) to have at the cloſe all the <hi>Judges</hi> preſent, to give their Opinion as to <hi>Dangerfield</hi>'s Teſtimony. Therefore to make ſhort work of it, which I ſaw would be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, I was willing the <hi>Ch. Juſtice</hi> ſhould preſently ſum up the <hi>Evidence;</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving begun, was interrupted by the <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney;</hi> for he told him, that he had ſomething to ſay. His <hi>Lordſhip</hi> deſiring him to be ſhort, <hi>becauſe the King had ſent for him,</hi> he urg'd, That there were two poſitive <hi>Witneſſes;</hi> that tho' ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might be objected againſt <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> yet <hi>Robberies</hi> were to be diſcover'd by <hi>Robbers,</hi> and <hi>Treaſon</hi> by <hi>Traitors;</hi> that notwithſtanding he had formerly been diſhoneſt, he might be otherwiſe now; and that <hi>Turner</hi> had prov'd his being at my Houſe in <hi>July</hi> or <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Upon this again I offer'd at my <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> but the <hi>Ch. Justice</hi> roſe up to be gone; therefore conſidering with my ſelf the former Reaſons, as alſo that my
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:97478:42"/>
                  <hi>Defence</hi> could be but natural Inferences, from what my <hi>Accuſers,</hi> or my own Witneſſes had affirmed, (which (me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought) might occur to any body at the bare ſumming up of things) I deſir'd his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> to ſtay, telling him, that I had done; and then he began to this effect:</p>
               <p>Firſt he told the <hi>Attorney,</hi> that, had he not interrupted him, yet he would have omitted nothing now mention'd, as being nicely careful when the <hi>King's</hi> Life is concern'd. Then he ſhow'd what <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> had alledg'd; and ſaid, I had thrown but little upon him by way of Infamy; For if the <hi>Verdict of Haſtings</hi> were material, every <hi>Witneſs</hi> muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd when a <hi>Jury</hi> goes againſt his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. That <hi>Hildeſley</hi> denies his coming over with him in the Pacquet Boat, but yet it was probable, that <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> was here, which I ſeem'd to admit. That the <hi>Jury</hi> muſt conſider things probable and inprobable, or elſe that the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of a <hi>Swearer</hi> might take away any man's life. That truly he underſtood not, how I could be ſo free, when <hi>Mr, Oates neither</hi> knew me, <hi>nor knows whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97478:42"/>I knew him;</hi> That <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> ſays to this; That, I muſt needs have ſeen that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> entruſted him, and therefore was the more confident of him, when I ſpoke ſo plainly to him in <hi>Mr. Fenwincks</hi> Chamber; but how far this <hi>Oath</hi> was to be taken, the <hi>Jury</hi> muſt conſider. That as for <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> tho' nothing infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous were prov'd againſt <hi>Oates,</hi> yet there was enough againſt him; That 'tis the Duty of a <hi>Judge</hi> to make juſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations to the <hi>Jury;</hi> That tho' a man may be a <hi>Witneſs in Law,</hi> yet they muſt conſider his <hi>Credit;</hi> That had he been only a <hi>Traytor,</hi> he had been as good a <hi>Witneſs</hi> as <hi>Oates,</hi> but that 6 <hi>Enormous Crimes</hi> are againſt him, and whether a <hi>man</hi> can preſently become a <hi>Saint</hi> by being a <hi>Witneſs,</hi> they were alſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider. That in diſproof of <hi>Dangerfield</hi> my <hi>Lady Powis</hi> and <hi>Mis. Cellier</hi> affirm'd no Letter was ſent from me; That it had been prov'd too, that I forbid him my Houſe in <hi>June</hi> or the begining of <hi>July,</hi> and that he then declared he had rather go 100 miles than come near me; which not only contradicts, what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, to wit, <hi>That I was never angry
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97478:43"/>with him before he refus'd the Treaſon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd by me;</hi> but ſhows alſo a great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probability, that I would be thus angry with him for going to the <hi>Tower</hi> in my name, and ſo angry alſo upon his refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to kill the <hi>King.</hi> That <hi>Turner</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not charge himſelf whether he were at my Houſe in <hi>June, July</hi> or <hi>Auguſt,</hi> but thinks only it was in <hi>July;</hi> That there was a great difference between <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> for one might be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, when perchance the other might not; That if two <hi>Witneſſes</hi> be produc'd, and one only of <hi>Credit,</hi> there is but one <hi>Witneſs</hi> to be reckon'd to the matter; and one was not enough to find a man <hi>Guilty of Treaſon;</hi> in which <hi>Opinion</hi> all the <hi>Judges</hi> did unanimouſly agree, and <hi>Mr, Juſtice Dolben</hi> added this, <hi>That ſince the Law required two Witneſſes that they must neceſſarily be both believed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this manner the <hi>Chief Juſtice</hi> ſum'd the Evidence which was approv'd of by the reſt; and tho' it were ſo clear, that he who afterwards ſhould have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd me, would have done it (I dare ſay) <hi>if one had riſen from the Dead,</hi> yet it was not (I muſt confeſs) all I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97478:43"/>eſpecially in relation to <hi>Mr. Oates,</hi> as I ſhall preſently ſhow the <hi>Reader.</hi> As ſoon then as <hi>his Lordſhip</hi> had ended, he went away, &amp; the <hi>Jury</hi> withdrew to their <hi>Chamber,</hi> where they remained ſo long, that it occaſion'd various diſcourſes and gueſſes all about; for ſome would have it an infallible ſign of my <hi>Condemnation;</hi> but others were of the contrary ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as thinking that too much haſte might diſparage the Plot, and raiſe doubts, whether what had already paſt, were well done. In fine (after above an hours ſtay) they returned, and no ſooner pronounced their <hi>Verdict,</hi> Not Guilty, but it was approv'd with a great <hi>ſhout</hi> over all the Hall, which was ſeconded by another in the <hi>Palace-yard;</hi> and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I muſt needs ſay, that I found every body extremely ſatisfied with my ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, as I paſt through the Crowd to my Coach. I mention not this, as if I thought any Catholick (and much leſs my ſelf) popular, but I do it to ſhow that no people are naturally ſo well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the preſervation of a <hi>Fellow-Subject,</hi> as <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> and conſequently how neceſſary it is to ferment their Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97478:44"/>and to put them quite beſides themſelves, before their humour can turn bloudy and inhumane.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the <hi>Particulars</hi> of my <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al;</hi> And now it will not be (I ſuppoſe) diſguſtful to the <hi>Reader,</hi> if I give him an Account (as I hinted before) of my intended <hi>Defence;</hi> for I took <hi>Notes</hi> all along, and ſo drew theſe plain and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious <hi>Deductions</hi> from the <hi>Premiſſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section__defence">
               <head>My Defence.</head>
               <p>THat of any <hi>Crime,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">My Defence.</note> I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thought <hi>Treaſon</hi> would be laid to my charge, who ſtill ran in a contrary career, as not a few about the <hi>King</hi> himſelf well knew. That I was not a little ſatisfi'd, (ſince 'twas my <hi>Fate</hi> to be accus'd) that my two <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> (as had been ſhown) were perſons well known to his <hi>Majesty</hi> and his Illuſtrious <hi>Council;</hi> the one in old Mr. <hi>Parker</hi>'s Caſe, to ſay no more of it; and the other a <hi>Forger of Treaſonable
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97478:44"/>Letters</hi> to entrap the Innocent, as <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield</hi>'s
<note n="*" place="margin">Oct 79. <hi>Dang.</hi> Nar. p. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>Commitment</hi> (by the <hi>Board</hi>) to <hi>Newgate,</hi> upon <hi>Col. Manſel</hi>'s account, tells the World in expreſs terms. That (in the 1ſt. place) as for <hi>Mr. Oates,</hi> who pretends to have been ſuch a Negotiator in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> where he perus'd and read my <hi>Letters,</hi> (and who makes himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſo neceſſary an Inſtrument, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nager here in <hi>England,</hi> that few, if any, conceal'd their <hi>Treaſon</hi> from him) it has been prov'd by his very <hi>School-fellows,</hi> that he was but an <hi>ordinary Scholar,</hi> both at <hi>Valladolid</hi> and St. <hi>Omers,</hi> going all that while to <hi>School</hi> as the reſt did, and continuing ſo to the day of his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. That at his return to <hi>London,</hi> (tho' it were in the heat of the <hi>Plot,</hi> and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal time of the <hi>Tranſactions</hi> in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) he is found to have been in the moſt lamentable and contemptible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that could be imagin'd; <hi>as tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing of</hi> common Papers <hi>towards a Livelihood; as getting</hi> Mr. Fenwick <hi>out of charity to pay ſometimes for his poor Lodging; as begging Alms at the</hi> Savoy <hi>in theſe his great and viſible neceſſities;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97478:45"/>and as being ſo little esteeem'd and valu'd by the</hi> Jeſuits, <hi>that they thought a</hi> Butler<hi>'s place a ſufficient preferment for him;</hi> Nay the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> were very many, that could prove this <hi>wretched Poverty</hi> of his, and he himſelf has confeſs'd it; a thing very ſtrange, ſuppoſing him only a <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> with ordinary men in an ordinary matter; but yet more wonderful, had he had (as he tells us) the Lives and Fortunes of the chiefeſt <hi>Catholicks</hi> thus hanging on his Lips. That as for Mr. <hi>Berry,</hi> if he were ever <hi>distemper'd in his Brain,</hi> it was not of late, I mean, <hi>ſince the Biſhop gave him the Cure of Souls, and leave to preach,</hi> as he preſently did upon his <hi>Recantation,</hi> (which was not long after the <hi>Diſcovery</hi> of the <hi>Plot</hi>) and yet then, he the ſaid Mr. <hi>Berry</hi> acquainted the <hi>King</hi> and his prime <hi>Ministers,</hi> with moſt of the preſent Particulars; After which Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> was pleas'd to be very kind to him both in money and fair words. That it was very improbable, that at the firſt daſh, and at the bare Recommendation of a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> I ſhould, without any neceſſity, communicate the higheſt <hi>Treaſon</hi> to a Stranger, <hi>who knew
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97478:45"/>not me, and with whom I never had any</hi> acquaintance, either before or after, as he himſelf acknowledg'd; and this alſo to one of no <hi>Garb,</hi> of no ſeeming extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary <hi>parts,</hi> and ſo mean alſo in his rank and condition, that I ſent him (as he himſelf ſays) to the <hi>general Poſt-houſe</hi> in <hi>London</hi> with a <hi>Letter:</hi> Nor is this <hi>Letter</hi> pretended to have Treaſon in it; for he tells us, that he only ſaw its <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription;</hi> and yet had it been of that nature, any <hi>Servant,</hi> any <hi>Footman</hi> of mine, or even any known <hi>Porter,</hi> might have been as well truſted with it as a <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Plotter,</hi> the main danger being at the <hi>Post-houſe,</hi> where <hi>Letters</hi> lye at ſix and ſevens, and are alſo often open'd in ſuſpitious times by Authority. That it was hardly credible for him <hi>not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi> (as he now ſwears) <hi>that he ſaid he had ſeen my Divorce,</hi> ſince he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly accus'd me of it <hi>four times;</hi> to wit, before the <hi>Commons;</hi> before the <hi>Justices of</hi> Weſtminſter, who by an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of that <hi>Houſe</hi> firſt committed me; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Judges</hi> of this <hi>Court,</hi> and before the <hi>King</hi> in <hi>Councel,</hi> even to my very face. That as to his coming over with
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97478:46"/>Mr. <hi>Hildeſley</hi> in <hi>April</hi> 78. Mr. <hi>Hildeſley</hi> not only denies it, but Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges, that he told him ſo in that very month, even when there could be no poſſible end or deſign in <hi>Hildeſley</hi> to lye; and Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi> is ſo far from a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of being ſuborn'd, that there are even <hi>Protestant Witneſſes</hi> of quality, to vouch his <hi>Evidence</hi> That it was very unlikely, that I ſhould inveigh in a <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of mine againſt the <hi>Seculars,</hi> ſince moſt of the <hi>Catholicks</hi> in <hi>Town,</hi> and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Protestants</hi> in <hi>Court</hi> will teſtifie, that none ever belong'd to me but a <hi>Secular;</hi> nor was the whole <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>Clergie</hi> otherwiſe than very kind to me both at home and abroad. That I call <hi>God</hi> to witneſs, that inſtead of Mr. <hi>Langworth</hi>'s recommending of Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> to me, or my ſpeaking <hi>Treaſon</hi> in his hearing, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard his <hi>Name</hi> mention'd, (that I know of) till after the <hi>Diſcovery</hi> of the <hi>Plot;</hi> nor ever ſaw his face, till I met him in this <hi>Court,</hi> even after my firſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment. That I hope my word (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving always liv'd with repute among my Acquaintance) ſhall be ſooner taken, than a man's who has already (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97478:46"/>by the Accuſation of <hi>young Parker</hi>) been cenſur'd and disbeliev'd even by Juries themſelves, where he was their Miniſter; and this upon account of evil practices, as I have ſhown, and as Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> wou'd have fully prov'd; nor ſhould I have fail'd of convicting him long ago of <hi>Perjury,</hi> had I not been hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd in it as aforeſaid. That Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s <hi>Falſhood,</hi> and conſequently my <hi>Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> reflects no more on the <hi>Votes</hi> of the two precedent <hi>Parliaments</hi> concerning the <hi>Plot,</hi> than it does on the Integrity of the <hi>Grand Jury,</hi> which found the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Bill;</hi> for as they could lawfully (upon <hi>Oath</hi> made) declare it <hi>Billa ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> and therefore that the Party accus'd ought to be try'd for his life, ſo the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> upon like Information might juſtly put the <hi>People</hi> upon their guard, and ſecuring the ſuſpected, call whom they pleas'd to the <hi>Bar of Justice,</hi> which was the intent and ſcope of that <hi>Vote.</hi> Neither could a <hi>Diſcovery</hi> or Detection of his ill <hi>Practices</hi> now, any ways ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign the <hi>Courts,</hi> that ſentenc'd Mr. <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> and the reſt, ſince <hi>Courts</hi> can do no more than hear, and afterwards judge,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97478:47"/>as verily they think and believe. That Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> has moſt evidently
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>N. B.</hi> Leſt any body ſhould queſtion whether Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> did thus contradict himſelf, the Reader is to know, that the Particulars are all mention'd, even by his Friend, the late Publiſher of this Tryal, as the Pages in the Margin ſhow.</note> 
                  <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted</hi> himſelf even in this <hi>Tryal,</hi> in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pag. 22</note> 
                  <hi>That he ſaw Letters of mine in</hi> Spain; for upon another queſtion, <hi>the</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>first he had ſeen, were (as near as he can remember) at St.</hi> Omers; and yet he went not thither, according to his own confeſſion, <hi>in</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeveral weeks after his Return from</hi> Spain. Beſides, the words, <hi>As near as I can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,</hi> confirm further the Abuſe, ſhowing us the whole Myſtery, and how the falſe-Step happen'd; <hi>viz.</hi> That the queſtion about the <hi>St.</hi> Omer <hi>Letters</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſual, and he having forgotten the <hi>Account</hi> given of his <hi>Spaniſh Intrigues,</hi> the Affirmation <hi>Yes,</hi> occurr'd next to his thoughts, adding to it only his uſual phraſe, <hi>As near as I can remember;</hi> for 'tis ſeldom or never that he is poſitive in any <hi>Anſwer,</hi> eſpecially if he be ſtrictly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97478:47"/>preſs'd and put to it. In the next place, (after that notorious Shuffle, <hi>of his not remembring, that he ſaid he had ſeen my Divorce)</hi> he mends the buſineſs with ſwearing, that part of our <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> at
<note n="(d)" place="margin">P. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Wild-houſe,</hi> was about that matter; as alſo, that he heard my <hi>Lord Caſtlemain</hi> ſay there, <hi>That he had been at great charge to carry on the buſineſs of the Divorce;</hi> and yet <hi>twice</hi> before he poſitively affirms, <hi>That he</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">P. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>knew me not at</hi> Wild-houſe. Again, To evade (if he could) Mr. <hi>Armſtrong</hi>'s material Evidence of his (the ſaid <hi>Oates</hi>'s) being but an <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Scholar</hi> at <hi>Valladolid; for he went to the ſame School with him and the reſt, and lived as the others did, without diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> nay Mr. <hi>Berry</hi> alſo, (by Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s own <hi>Letters</hi>) witneſs'd the ſame thing: I ſay, to avoid this, he would have it, <hi>That, by the deſires, forſooth, of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, he went only twice or thrice to ſhow them the way to School;</hi> which is ſo wild an Invention, that it equals any contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction whatſoever; for how can a man imagine, that the <hi>Fathers</hi> ſhould ſend a <hi>Stranger,</hi> and one alſo that came to <hi>treat</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:97478:48"/>and <hi>conſult</hi> about <hi>Affairs of State,</hi> and things of the higheſt conſequence, to ſhow <hi>young Scholars</hi> the <hi>Logick School,</hi> when as the meaneſt wretch in the <hi>Houſe</hi> could do it as well, and better; nor was the employment fit for any other. And as one ſtumble ſtill occaſions more, ſo this puts Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> upon averring, that He taught the Youths their <hi>Philoſophical Dictates:</hi> a moſt excellent and appoſite <hi>Office</hi> for an <hi>Extraordinary Envoy,</hi> and more eſpecially when every body that knows him, knows what a <hi>Philoſopher</hi> and <hi>Clerk</hi> he is.</p>
               <p>To conclude then with him; That I do again and again recommend to my Jury's Conſideration his Procedure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Parkers,</hi> as a thing which Hiſtory can never paſs by, and which muſt moſt evidently ſhow them what a man he is; for if a <hi>Witneſs</hi> has already in a criminal Charge been found by a <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of his Neighbours and Acquaintance to be of a malicious humour, to alledge Particulars that ſeveral of known Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity have diſprov'd, and conſequently that he was not to be believ'd, what <hi>Jury</hi> that is convinc'd of the ſaid Procedure,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97478:48"/>can afterwards depend on his bare Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in an Accuſation of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, eſpecially when it is as apparent as the day, how far his Intereſt as well as Malice is thereby gratify'd.</p>
               <p>Now for <hi>Dangerfield</hi> he is ſo noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ſcandalous, that there is no man perchance in <hi>England</hi> againſt whom there have been more <hi>recorded Villanies;</hi> produced; ſo that if the Law ſtops not his mouth, yet his many nefarious crimes have taken all <hi>Credit</hi> from him; That (among his great and ſundry Tranſgreſſions) he has already been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed and puniſh'd for falſly accuſing <hi>Col. Manſel of Treaſon,</hi> and if he has been once thus faulty, why not again, eſpecially ſince there is nothing but his own proſtituted word to make good his Accuſation? That I had no manner of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with him, but as he was ſent on Ordinary Errands by <hi>Mrs. Cellier, viz.</hi> for the weekly Allowance to the <hi>poor Priſoners,</hi> for the boarding of my <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> who lay at her Houſe, and the like. That finding that he went to the <hi>Earl of Powis</hi> and others at the <hi>Tower</hi> in my name, about Printing the <hi>Jeſuits
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:97478:49"/>Speeches,</hi> I fell out with <hi>Mrs. Cellier,</hi> and told her, <hi>That if ever he came again to my Houſe I would have him kickt;</hi> That this great diſpleaſure of mine was not only confeſs'd by <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> when I was examin'd by the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Councel,</hi> but is proved now both by <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> and <hi>Mr. Duddel,</hi> whom He (the ſaid <hi>Dangerfield</hi>) complain'd of it to; That 'tis incredible that I ſhould preſently talk <hi>Treaſon,</hi> to one whom I had ſo ſeverely treated; and 'tis yet more incredible, that I ſhould be thus open to him, and then terrifie him with my words and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures ſo, as to make him (as he ſwears) run down Stairs, and to be gone for good and all. That it is a falſhood, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction too, to ſay, <hi>He was taken out of Newgate by the Lords in the Tower to kill the King,</hi> ſince his firſt admittance to them was long after, and this alſo by a trick, <hi>viz.</hi> a pretended meſſage in my name, which made me ſo angry with him <hi>that I threatned to have him kickt</hi> (as <hi>aforeſaid</hi>) <hi>if ever he came near me more.</hi> Beſides how ridiculous it is, to ſay, that the <hi>Lords</hi> (were they the greateſt <hi>Traytors</hi> in the World) would propoſe to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:97478:49"/>an unknown Fellow ſuch a <hi>Deſign,</hi> who was ſure of a better reward by diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it, than they could give for doing it. That it is a prodigious and unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd Impudence, and of a ſad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence alſo, to have a <hi>Witneſs</hi> thus mince and inlarge his Evidence at pleaſure; for at the <hi>Councel</hi> when I was Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he only charg'd me with being angry with him for not doing what the <hi>Lords propoſed,</hi> but never ſaid, I expreſs'd what the <hi>Propoſal</hi> was; whereas he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes me at preſent of abſolutely confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to be <hi>the killing of his Majeſty,</hi> tho it be non-ſence and incredible, as has been ſhown; and that his former <hi>Accuſation</hi> was only thus, I appeal not only to his
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>vid. Dang. Nar. p.</hi> 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Narrative,</hi> but to the <hi>King</hi> himſelf and all the <hi>Lords</hi> that attended him there in <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel.</hi> That 'tis evident that <hi>Dangerfield</hi> calls for <hi>Counter-Witneſſes</hi> only to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and to perplex (if he could) the buiſineſs, for <hi>Woodman</hi> was ſent (we ſee) by <hi>Mrs. Cellier</hi> or her <hi>Daughter;</hi> and the 3 <hi>l.</hi> brought by him was not for <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield,</hi> but the <hi>Priſoners. Turner</hi> alſo knows not the time when he ſaw him at
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:97478:50"/>my Houſe; for 'tis ſometimes in <hi>June,</hi> ſometimes in <hi>July;</hi> which is nothing to <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the month when <hi>Dangerfield</hi> ſwear's to have heard this <hi>Treaſon.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther does <hi>Turner</hi> ſay, <hi>he ſaw me and</hi> Dangerfield <hi>together, but that he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting below;</hi> and who can tell had this been as late as <hi>July</hi> but he might come to ſpeak with one of my <hi>Foot-boys?</hi> That it is falſe he ever carri'd <hi>Letters</hi> from me to the <hi>Counteſs of Powis,</hi> and ſhe her ſelf denies it, a <hi>Lady</hi> even more eminent for her known <hi>Probity</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi> than for her great Quality and Birth.</p>
               <p>That laſtly, it is a moſt apparent <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, that I did teach the St.</hi> Omer <hi>Youths, what they were to witneſs;</hi> for <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> in <hi>Court</hi> can teſtifie, that being ſent to St. <hi>Omers</hi> about <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> 78. to know whether Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> had been there all <hi>April</hi> and <hi>May,</hi> as was aſſerted in Mr. <hi>Ireland</hi>'s <hi>Tryal,</hi> they found it confirm'd by the whole <hi>Colledge,</hi> and ſaw <hi>fourteen</hi> of the chief <hi>Scholars</hi> (among which was <hi>Gifford</hi>) make <hi>Oath</hi> before the <hi>City Magiſtrates, That the ſaid</hi> Oates <hi>never lay out of the Colledge from the</hi> 10th <hi>of</hi> Dec. 77. <hi>to the</hi> 23 <hi>of</hi> June <hi>following,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:97478:50"/>but one night at</hi> Watten; <hi>for that he the ſaid</hi> Oates <hi>ſitting at a diſtinct Table in the Refectory, and reading every Sunday and Holiday all</hi> April, May, <hi>and part of</hi> June <hi>in the Sodality, could not poſſibly be abſent, (as he pretended) without every bodies ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king notice of it.</hi> Nor can this <hi>Teſtimony</hi> be invented by me to ſerve a preſent Turn, ſince the then <hi>Certificate</hi> of the <hi>Premiſſes</hi> (under the very Seal of that <hi>City</hi>) is not only here in <hi>Court,</hi> but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the <hi>Compendium</hi> before ever I was accus'd by <hi>Dangerfield;</hi> Nay, which is more, in the <hi>Letter</hi> from <hi>Mons,</hi> a <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet</hi> of a much longer ſtanding (as da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Febr.</hi> 19.78. <hi>old ſtile</hi>) and publick ſeveral weeks here in <hi>Town,</hi> before ever the ſaid <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was ſo much as ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of <hi>Priſon;</hi> for that happen'd not till <hi>April,</hi> as appears by his own
<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Narrative.</hi> All which evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently proves, that had thoſe <hi>Youths</hi> (who were moſt of them alſo Lads of the upper Forms) been really taught what they had affirm'd at the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> they had their <hi>Leſſon</hi> beyond Sea, and not from me.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:97478:51"/>
               <p>This was the effect of my <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">My further Witneſſes.</note> and truly tho' I had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided <hi>Witneſſes</hi> to clear my ſelf in every ſmall particular, yet I found ſuch trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, at leaſt towards the latter end of the <hi>Tryal,</hi> (when any pretence of tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, or impertinence could be obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) that I thought it alſo fit to omit the calling of them, notwithſtanding they were <hi>legally ſummon'd,</hi> and ready in the <hi>Hall</hi> or <hi>Court,</hi> as my <hi>Sollicitors</hi> inform'd me. For firſt, I had ſubpoena'd Sir <hi>John Nicholas,</hi> who was preſent at my <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> before the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> and could have conſequently confirm'd (had it been needful) Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> and Mr. <hi>Duddels</hi> Teſtimony; for <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> had acknowledg'd at the <hi>Board,</hi> That I had forbidden him my Houſe at his going to the <hi>Tower</hi> in my name, as I formerly mention'd; and Sir <hi>John</hi> could not but know alſo, that <hi>Oates</hi> had ſworn there, the ſeeing of my <hi>Divorce,</hi> &amp;c. Secondly, Mr. <hi>Cellier</hi> was cited; for he could teſtifie, that being by when I chid his Wife, I had forbidden her from ever ſending <hi>Dangerfield</hi> to me more. 3ly. Mr. <hi>Gadbury,</hi> who could witneſs, that he
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:97478:51"/>never had any diſcourſe with <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> about me, and thereby I ſhould have ſhewn how falſly he had averr'd in his
<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Dang.</hi> firſt Nar. p. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Narrative, That the ſaid Mr.</hi> Gadbury <hi>was angry with him becauſe he had diſpleaſed (by his ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity) the Lords in the Tower, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially me, who had deſign'd to advance him, and help to make his Fortune.</hi> 4ly. I had ſent to Mr. <hi>Nevil</hi> (whom <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> calls <hi>my true Second, and one from whom I had Papers</hi>) to atteſt, That I never receiv'd Paper from him in his life, nor ſent him any; as alſo that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſulted with him about, or ſpoke to him of any <hi>Affidavits,</hi> nor of any other matters that related to <hi>Lane</hi> or <hi>Knox,</hi> tho' <hi>Dangerfield</hi> had accus'd me of it in their <hi>Tryal.</hi> 5ly. <hi>Justice Foſter</hi> to prove (as I heard he had done before the <hi>Councel</hi>) a <hi>Forgery</hi> committed by <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> ſince his very Pardon and his being one of the <hi>Kings Witneſſes;</hi> for he had it ſeems ſhewn one <hi>Hill</hi> an <hi>Affidavit</hi> to ſwear to, and then preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>enterlining</hi> it with ſome matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Duke,</hi> brought the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> to take his <hi>Oath</hi> before this <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:97478:52"/>who like a worthy man, reading firſt the <hi>Paper</hi> to him, diſcover'd the Villany. I intended alſo to have had Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in <hi>Court,</hi> had he not then been in <hi>Execution</hi> in the <hi>Fleet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Verdict</hi> being thus given in,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cheek</hi>'s Pretences.</note> as I have ſaid, I deſir'd a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of mine to go to the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Jury,</hi> and to acquaint them from me, that being extremely <hi>ſenſible</hi> how tired they muſt needs be, I ſhould take it as a very particular Obligation, if they would let him attend them to ſome <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern,</hi> till I could come my ſelf and wait upon them. This he did, and in the mean while I ſtaid at the <hi>Bar,</hi> expecting my <hi>Diſcharge;</hi> which going to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd, Mr. <hi>Cheek</hi> roſe up and told the <hi>Court, that I had not yet paid my Fees:</hi> Whereupon the <hi>Judges</hi> ſaying, that was a neceſſary <hi>Duty,</hi> I anſwer'd, I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready perform'd it. Mr. <hi>Cheek</hi> or his Counſel reply'd, That what I had paid to Sir <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> was nothing to him. <hi>My Lords,</hi> (ſaid I) No <hi>Priſoner</hi> is to pay but once; nor have I been any more than once ſo; for I was only upon Bail, and therefore never diſcharg'd ſince
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:97478:52"/>my firſt going to the <hi>Tower.</hi> The <hi>Judges</hi> upon this, ſtopt a little, and after a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſpeaking together, Mr. <hi>Juſtice Dolben</hi> told me, that I was twice <hi>commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and for that reaſon I muſt pay my <hi>Fee</hi> again. Pray my <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaid I, let my <hi>Counſel</hi> argue the Point, and beſides, what is the <hi>Fee</hi> I muſt pay, if it be due? We know not that, (reply'd Mr. Juſtice <hi>Dolben</hi>) but this we muſt tell you, you cannot be diſcharg'd till your <hi>Fees</hi> are paid; and ſo they roſe, leaving <hi>Mr. Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant</hi> and me in diſpute; for he told me, that he would carry me to the <hi>Tower</hi> again, unleſs he were ſatisfy'd: and my anſwer was, <hi>Let him do it at his peril.</hi> In ſhort, after ſome words on both ſides, he commanded the <hi>Gentleman-Jayler,</hi> and the <hi>Warders</hi> that attended, to bring me back on pain of their <hi>Suſpenſion;</hi> and then going out of the Court, I went from the <hi>Bar</hi> directly to the <hi>Fleece,</hi> where I underſtood my <hi>Jury</hi> were.</p>
               <p>When I came up, I ſaluted them, and then ſpoke to this effect: That tho' I were not to thank them for their Juſtice, which notwithſtanding I ſhould never forget, yet I was to acknowledge the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:97478:53"/>preſent <hi>favonr</hi> which brought me thus acquainted with ſo many extraordinary <hi>Perſons,</hi> whom I had never ſo much as once ſeen before. Their return was like themſelves, and as obliging as could be imagin'd; but nothing pleas'd me more, than that they ſeem'd unanimouſly to own me not only a <hi>free man,</hi> but an <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man</hi> alſo. I deſir'd <hi>Mr. Johnſon</hi> too in particular, to believe that it was not out of any Diſlike or ill Opinion of him, that I made ſome little heſitation and ſtop at his being called to the Book; for that I had (I aſſured him) as great a value for him, as any of his Friends and Servants could have. He anſwer'd, that he was exceedingly ſatisfy'd with my carriage, and was conſident alſo that the two other <hi>Gentlemen</hi> (whom I had accidentally paſs'd by) were of the ſame ſentiment. Not long after, and when we had all ſeated our ſelves, a <hi>Gentleman</hi> of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (who was a friend both to <hi>Mr. Cheek</hi> and me) came to us, and deſiring ſome few words aſide, he told me, that to a void noiſe, this difference muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated. I anſwer'd him, That the time of doing it was paſt, it being
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:97478:53"/>already as publick as it could be; and therefore I ſhould now ſee what the <hi>Law</hi> ſaid in the <hi>Caſe,</hi> for if any thing were due to him, he ſhould have it to the utmoſt Farthing, if not, his bringing me to the <hi>Tower</hi> (a place I had no averſion to for a night, and eſpecially when it was to try an Experiment) might be a greater inconvenience to him than he was aware of. When he had done, I told the <hi>Company,</hi> ſince they were the prime men of the <hi>County,</hi> (and that therefore moſt buſineſs came before them) I ſhould again, I believ'd, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them with ſome Concerns of mine; and then gave an Account of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of this Affair. They anſwer'd, that certainly the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> was ill advis'd, for that I had been (as they yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd) but once a <hi>Priſoner,</hi> ſo that there could be but one <hi>Fee</hi> due.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, after an agreeable Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſeveral hours with theſe worthy <hi>Patriots,</hi> (for their Diſcourſe ſtill tended to the intereſt and advantage of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) we parted, and then I ſent for the <hi>Gentleman-Jaylor</hi> and the <hi>Warders,</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them that I would go to the <hi>Tower,</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:97478:54"/>if they durſt carry me. They anſwer'd, that they hop'd I would not be offended with them, ſeeing what they did was in Obedience to their <hi>Superior's commands.</hi> I reply'd, That every <hi>Command of a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior</hi> was not to be obey'd;
<note place="margin">I return'd to the <hi>Tower.</hi>
                  </note> and then calling for my Coach, and taking the <hi>Gentleman-Jaylor</hi> with me (the reſt following in others) they brought me to my <hi>Lodging,</hi> but put no <hi>Sentinel</hi> in the Night-time at the door as formerly. In the morning I ſent to <hi>Mr. Cheek</hi> to know if my preſent Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were by his Orders. He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Yes,</hi> I reſolv'd to ſtay all that day, and by accident I did ſo the next alſo; for he was gone, before I was up, to <hi>Windſor,</hi> and return'd not till it was very late.</p>
               <p>The day following (being Saturday the 26 of <hi>June</hi>) I went after Dinner to his Houſe, and told him, I was come to bid him Adieu, not doubting alſo but he would excuſe me, if out of Curioſity I askt why he had thus detain'd me a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner? He anſwer'd, becauſe I had not paid him my <hi>Fees,</hi> and that the <hi>Judges</hi> themſelves had (as I ſaw) declar'd they
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:97478:54"/>could not diſcharge me till this were done. I reply'd, that he well knew (I ſuppos'd) the reaſon of my Refuſal; to wit, <hi>becauſe I had paid them before;</hi> that the <hi>Judges</hi> thought not fit to hear my <hi>Councel</hi> argue the matter, nor to tell me what theſe <hi>Fees</hi> were; that if his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure were juſtifiable, it was well; and that (as for my own part) having done what I thought very convenient, I had no more to ſay, but to ask, what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of me? He anſwer'd, that being a <hi>Peer</hi> there was 100 <hi>l.</hi> due to him; 10 <hi>l.</hi> to the Gentleman Porter, and 5 <hi>l.</hi> to the Gentleman Jaylor. I ſaid, that by my <hi>Tryal</hi> he found I was no <hi>Peer</hi> in Law; and that, tho' few ever refus'd to be kind to the <hi>Gentleman Jaylor,</hi> yet a <hi>Fee</hi> for him I believ'd was never exacted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. He reply'd, that I was a <hi>Peer;</hi> that my <hi>Lord Aſton</hi> had paid 100 <hi>l.</hi> and that what he demanded for the <hi>Gentleman Jaylor</hi> was his due; I told him that I was ſo far from diſputing his demands, that if he requir'd yet more, it ſhould be paid him, and that I would take my own time to examine the Legality. Then deſiring him to order ſome body (as he
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:97478:55"/>did) to receive thoſe ſums of my <hi>Steward</hi> at my Lodging, we parted; and ſo I went to take my leave of the <hi>Lords,</hi> whilſt the money was telling. Within ſome little time after (when I thought all was done) my <hi>Secretary</hi> came to me, and ſaid that <hi>Mr. Cheek</hi> refus'd to ſign an <hi>Acquittance,</hi> which had caus'd my <hi>Steward</hi> to take back the money: I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd him to go to my <hi>Councel</hi> forthwith, and know what ſhould be further done; who ſent me word, that tho' every body look'd upon one as a ſtrange Man that refus'd ſo reaſonable a thing as an <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance,</hi> yet the Law obliged none to it, therefore <hi>Witneſſes</hi> would be as good as his hand. Hearing this, I ſent him back to <hi>Mr. Cheek</hi> to tell him, he might have the money, ſince my <hi>Councel</hi> had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd me, that <hi>Witneſſes</hi> were as much to my purpoſe, as what was before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd. He anſwer'd, that ſo he had his dues, I might have as many as I pleas'd; upon which the money was paid him, and preſently I took <hi>Coach</hi> and went home. This is the account of what paſs'd between the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> and me; and ſince it was a very publick buſineſs, and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:97478:55"/>one alſo that may again come upon the Stage, I thought it not amiſs to inform the <hi>Reader</hi> with all the particulars that relate to it.</p>
               <p>Having thus far put an end to the troubles which <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Dangerfield</hi> created me, I continu'd a while in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> about my private Affairs, and then went down to my <hi>Brother</hi>'s near <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor;</hi> where I determin'd to ſtay till <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> or thereabouts,
<note place="margin">1680.</note> as the quieteſt and beſt time in Winter to paſs the Seas. But the <hi>Parliament</hi> (aſſembling in <hi>October</hi>) ſat not long, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I heard of <hi>Turbervile</hi>'s odd Charge againſt me, ſpecified ſoon after to this effect, in his printed <hi>Narratives:</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Firſt Nar. p. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>That he and ſeveral Priests were at Conſults with me at</hi> Powis <hi>Caſtle;</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. p. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>That being with my Lord</hi> Powis <hi>in</hi> Vereſtreet, <hi>he heard me (about</hi> May 78.) <hi>ſay Maſs;</hi> and
<note n="*" place="margin">2d. Nar. p. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>That he had alſo been at Confeſſion with me.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering therefore, that the <hi>Term</hi> was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready begun; that <hi>Papiſt</hi> it ſelf was no good name; that <hi>Prieſt</hi> was a worſe; and that ſhould I chance to be confin'd
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:97478:56"/>on this <hi>Information,</hi> I muſt neceſſarily continue ſo, to the end of <hi>Hilary Term,</hi> I thought it beſt to begin my intended Journey, and ſo with what convenient haſte I could, I came over.</p>
               <p>This then is Mr. <hi>Turber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile</hi>'s Accuſation,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Turbervile</hi>'s Falſhood about my being at <hi>Pewis</hi> Caſtle.</note> but how weak and idle, is evident by the very firſt part of it; to wit, his Allegation, <hi>That I was at Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults with him at</hi> Powis <hi>Caſtle,</hi> and yet I have not been ſo much as within thoſe Walls, ſince the great <hi>Plague</hi> in 65. which is ſeven years before his admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance into that Family; for he came not there till
<note n="*" place="margin">2d. Nar. p. 2.</note> 72. even according to his ſecond <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection,</hi> which he call'd 73. in the
<note n="*" place="margin">Firſt Nar. p. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>firſt</hi> Depoſitions. Now that what I affirm is true, appears by my Lord <hi>Powis</hi>'s Daughter the Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> (on whom he waited) who can depoſe, that ſhe neither ſaw me, nor believes me to have been there, ſince the time afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. In the like manner by my Lady <hi>Frances,</hi> and my Lady <hi>Anne,</hi> her two Siſters; by Sir <hi>John Gifford,</hi> who liv'd there a great while, and by all <hi>my Lords
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:97478:56"/>Gentlemen,</hi> and the principal <hi>Officers</hi> of his Family; by the <hi>Steward of my own Eſtate</hi> in that County, who dwells near, and very often comes there; and laſtly, by my <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Relations</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> that ſtill knew from time to time where I was. I will alſo appeal to all the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of Montgomeryſhire,</hi> (moſt of whom I have the happineſs to be known to, and to ſome nearly related) whether ever they ſaw me in thoſe parts ſince the before-mentioned year. I will alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> and <hi>chief Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of Pool,</hi> a place not only in, and about which my <hi>Estate</hi> lies, and my <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants</hi> live, but ſo near the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> that it joyns in a manner to the <hi>Park Pale;</hi> ſo that a Stranger, that comes to <hi>my Lord's,</hi> is as much ſeen and talk'd of by them, as if he lodg'd in the Town it ſelf. Nor can any body (tho' he conſiders as little as Mr. <hi>Turbervile</hi>) pretend that I was there privately intriguing; for no mad man would draw a certain ſuſpicion on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by a diſcovery, (which muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily happen in a vaſt Family, and in a Country where I was well known) when my publick appearing could raiſe
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:97478:57"/>in no Creature the leaſt jealouſie, having Concerns there to look after, and a <hi>Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> and <hi>Friend</hi> to viſit. Beſides, I can poſitively prove by ſeveral of Note and Credit, where I was any particular week theſe many years; for my being almoſt always out of <hi>England</hi> makes it eaſie, and beyond the reach of Diſpute or Difference.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, that coming to <hi>Paris</hi> about <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> 71. and receiving there Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from a <hi>great Nobleman,</hi> about a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, (publick enough afterwards) I ſtept over to <hi>London</hi> to wait upon him; but as I was again returning, (and had taken even leave of my Friends in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral) there befel my <hi>Brother Sir Philip Palmer</hi> ſome Troubles, which (as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthy men of the <hi>Long Robe</hi> well know) forc'd me to a very tedious ſtay, before I could compoſe them; nor did I during my whole abode in <hi>England,</hi> (which was ſomewhat above a twelve-month) lye two nights together out of Town, (as not a few can witneſs) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in <hi>October</hi> 72. when I went with ſome <hi>Relations</hi> to my ſaid <hi>Brother's</hi> Houſe, and there I alſo ſtay'd leſs than a
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:97478:57"/>week. Nay ſo far was I from going into <hi>Wales,</hi> that my <hi>Steward</hi> brought me up my <hi>Accounts</hi> at the end of that year, and ſeveral of my <hi>Montgomeryſhire Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> were pleas'd to come and ſee me, and among others my late <hi>Lord Herbert of Cherbury;</hi> ſo that had I been near him, I ſhould not have fail'd in what I was always wont to do, <hi>viz.</hi> of viſiting his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> when I came into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. But the Myſtery of Mr. <hi>Turber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi>'s Story is, (for all <hi>Fables</hi> have their <hi>Mythologie</hi>) that a <hi>Brother</hi> of mine was a great part of the year 73. at <hi>Powis-Castle,</hi> as the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of that <hi>County</hi> can atteſt. I ſpeak not this as if Mr. <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berville</hi> miſtook the one for the other, but to ſhow what gave the hints to his fancy; and certainly had I been there, I could not be ſuch a fool, (tho' <hi>Papiſts</hi> be the weakeſt men alive, if we judge by what is ſaid of them) as to deny it thus poſitively, when ſo many <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> of repute and quality (whom I call upon) muſt needs riſe in judgment againſt me; and when the thing in it ſelf, even with Mr. <hi>Turbervill</hi>'s Comment to it, cannot affect or prejudice me, <hi>who
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:97478:58"/>have been try'd and acquitted of all Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons relating to the Plot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for my being a <hi>Priest,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of my being a Prieſt.</note> (which at one time or other muſt be known, if I be one) I do not only poſitively deny it, but lay the <hi>Lye</hi> on the <hi>Tenets of my Religion,</hi> which doubtleſs I would not do, when <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> (they ſay) are ſo concern'd for its honour and intereſt, that they will die with an Untruth in their mouths, tho' it be (as we all confeſs and declare) <hi>a damnable act, and a ſin equal to that againſt the Holy Ghost.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place,
<note place="margin">Of my ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſs.</note> Whereas Mr. <hi>Turberville</hi> will have it, <hi>That I ſaid Maſs to my Lord</hi> Powis <hi>at his Lodging in</hi> Vere-ſtreet, I will be bound, that not only my <hi>Lord,</hi> my <hi>Lady,</hi> their <hi>Children,</hi> their chiefeſt <hi>Attendants,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Percy,</hi> (the <hi>Master</hi> of the Houſe in <hi>Vere-ſtreet</hi>) but any <hi>five, ten,</hi> or <hi>twenty,</hi> of the prime <hi>Catholicks of Quality</hi> in <hi>England</hi> ſhall atteſt, that they have been ſo far from hearing my <hi>Maſs,</hi> that they verily believe (for ſeveral weighty Reaſons) that I am not in <hi>Orders.</hi> Now that I ſhould impart this Secret to ſuch a
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:97478:58"/>man as <hi>Turberville,</hi> who confeſſes upon <hi>Oath,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Firſt Narrat. p. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>That he made his Fſcape out of the Monaſtery he had entred into,</hi> which ſhows how ſlight and unſteady a perſon he was, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently how little <hi>zeal</hi> he had for his <hi>Religion</hi> in general: I ſay, that I ſhould impart this <hi>Secret</hi> to ſuch a man, and not to my beſt Friends and Acquaintance, is an <hi>Imagination</hi> that becomes ſuch a Witneſs.</p>
               <p>But to come yet cloſer to the buſineſs, Mr. <hi>Turberville</hi> and I have been ſo far from this wonderful intimacy and dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>That I protest I never ſaw him to my knowledge.</hi> And becauſe the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and others in his preſent Poſt and Station, have often in reſerve ſome poor forlorn wretch, (for I'le caſt my ſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Oath of any man of Repute and Eſtate) to vouch a by-Circumſtance, which they know will be deni'd. I ſhall now prove this my Aſſertion, not only by the afore-named Teſtimony of my <hi>Lord Powis,</hi> my <hi>Lady,</hi> their <hi>Children,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>beſt Note</hi> in their <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> but by all my own <hi>Servants</hi> alſo; nay by <hi>two</hi> of Mr. <hi>Turberville</hi>'s <hi>Brothers,</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:97478:59"/>and by ſeveral of Credit that know me and him, with the manner of his Life and Actions. For all theſe can and will teſtifie, that they never ſaw, heard, nor yet believe, that he had the leaſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe or Acquaintance with me; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if his Tale were in any degree true, 'twould be impoſſible that they ſhould be all ignorant of it, eſpecially, <hi>having been</hi> (as he ſwears) <hi>together at Powis-Castle;</hi> and ſeeing alſo that my own <hi>Domeſticks</hi> muſt take notice (either ſooner or later) of thoſe that have any thing to do with me. Nor is it to be pretended even by Mr. <hi>Turberville</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, (notwithſtanding the great quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Invention) that ſtill he came <hi>incognito,</hi> and by ſtealth to me; for how weak and ſilly muſt it appear to any child to hear it ſaid, that we (forſooth) were thus cautious, and made ſo many grimaçes, and good morrows, when thoſe who are at preſent moſt charged with <hi>plotting,</hi> converſed always as open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together, as Friends, Neighbours, and Correſpondents uſually do. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>ſuper totam materiam,</hi> to ſpeak in a <hi>Schoolman</hi>'s phraſe, (and by the <hi>Orders</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:97478:59"/>given me, he has made me a piece of one) does not this his Evidence qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drate and agree with his former <hi>ſolemn Depoſition;</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Firſt Nar. p. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>That his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Enemies (by reaſon of his leaving his Monaſtery) got at laſt his Brother</hi> (who alſo ſerv'd my <hi>Lord Powis) to diſinherit him;</hi> whenas not only his ſaid <hi>Brother</hi> (as a bare Borderer on <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty)</hi> may have Children enough before his death; but he himſelf, (I mean, Mr. <hi>Turberville</hi> our Witneſs) is only a <hi>fifth Brother,</hi> and which is leſs, a <hi>third</hi> by a <hi>ſecond Venter;</hi> ſo that a <hi>Lawyer</hi> of an ordinary ſize may tell us, what an <hi>Heir at Law</hi> he is (according to the cuſtom of <hi>England</hi>) to this Eſtate, had none of the intermediate <hi>Brothers</hi> any Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>Nay let the whole World judge, even the moſt partial men breathing, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mr. <hi>Turberville,</hi> that <hi>ran away from his Monastery,</hi> that had no <hi>zeal for his Religion,</hi> that <hi>liv'd ſharking</hi> ever ſince, that has <hi>turn'd Protestant,</hi> at leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Diſcovery, <hi>(for he was then actually ſent down to</hi> Glamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganſhire <hi>to catch Prieſts</hi>) would not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:97478:60"/>all <hi>Encouragements</hi> from the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> from the <hi>King's reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Proclamations,</hi> and from the whole <hi>people</hi> in general, ſuffer me, who was impriſon'd from the beginning, and at laſt try'd for my life, to be legally and publickly acquitted, if his preſent <hi>Charge</hi> had been then thought of.</p>
               <p>But tho' not one <hi>Judge</hi> perchance in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> could, (bating the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt which people might juſtly have of the Charge) <hi>prove himſelf no Prieſt,</hi> if a Villain would point blanck ſwear it, yet I can by God's Providence, (beſides what has already been alledg'd) make, <hi>à priori,</hi> the falſhood of this Accuſation evident; and thus I ſhould have done long ago, had it been grateful at my <hi>Tryal,</hi> to ſhow Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s ſmall miſtake about the <hi>Divorce;</hi> for the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that demonſtrate the untruth of the one, would have done the ſame to the other; and then Mr. <hi>Turberville</hi> had had a Buoy or Light-houſe to guide him from this Shallow, on which he has at laſt ſo ſtrangely and childiſhly ſtranded.
<note place="margin">The Grounds of the Fancy.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now that the <hi>Reader</hi> may alſo underſtand the Grounds
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:97478:60"/>of this Fancy, and how it had its Riſe, he is to know, that reſolving with my ſelf, (ſome 7 years ſince) not to marry again, ſhould it be never ſo much in my power; and conſidering too, that it was the beſt time to ſettle my <hi>Brother,</hi> (or <hi>Heir</hi> at <hi>Law</hi>) in the World, if I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him any real and ſolid advantage, by what might at length fall unto him, I thought fit to give him, and ſome others of my <hi>Relations,</hi> the greateſt part of my <hi>Eſtate in preſent,</hi> with the reſt in <hi>Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and then married him to his, and my own ſatisfaction. This being look'd upon by many as an unuſual Action, and ſome reflecting, that I (who took ſo much pleaſure in travelling) was now retired, and diverted my ſelf in turning over <hi>Books,</hi> and the like; as alſo that my Lady <hi>Cleveland</hi> had withdrawn her ſelf ſome few years after into a <hi>Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> (which is the common method of married people in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> that intend to change their ſtate of life) it preſently became bruited, <hi>that I was, or ſhortly would be in Orders.</hi> No won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then if Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> made this a part of his <hi>Accuſation;</hi> and by the way I muſt
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:97478:61"/>tell him, (that in my poor judgment) 'tis not only the chief flower of his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, to wit, the beſt grounded Charge, that ever yet came from him, but alſo manag'd with the moſt caution and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, qualities (as many think) not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry natural to him; for he has here only ſworn, (as I ſhow'd before) <hi>That he ſaw Letters (forſooth) ſignifying my ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſs,</hi> and therefore could not be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſproved, were he never ſo much the Inventer of the Story. But if Mr. <hi>Turberville</hi> has been more bold and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and thereby run himſelf, (as I ſaid) on ground, he may yet urge this for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; That (being engag'd, perhaps, by the prevalent Entreaty of ſpecial <hi>Friends</hi> to accuſe me) He was neceſſitated to this poor <hi>Topick</hi> of a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> ſeeing the Law had already acquitted me of the <hi>Plot;</hi> for otherwiſe we ſhould have had, (I warrant you) wonderful Particulars in Print from ſome or other, not only of late <hi>Conſults at Powis-Caſtle,</hi> (tho' I have not been there, as I mention'd, theſe 15 years) but of a conſtant correſpondency with him in his <hi>Noviceſhip at Doway,</hi> in his <hi>French Expedition,</hi> and in all his other <hi>Adventures</hi> alſo.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:97478:61"/>
               <p>To end then with this <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Several Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſworn to be <hi>Prieſts.</hi>
                  </note> I do here again pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and declare, <hi>that his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation against me, is falſe, both in part and in the whole;</hi> and yet it is not to be wondred at as ſtrange, ſeeing <hi>Priesthood</hi> has of late been ſworn againſt other <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> as well as my ſelf; for upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and <hi>Oates</hi>'s <hi>Oath, Mr. Preſton</hi> (as every body knows) was dragged from his very <hi>Wife</hi> into <hi>Priſon,</hi> where he lay above 18 months; and <hi>old Mr. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen</hi> (who had been but few years a <hi>Widower,</hi> and never out of <hi>England)</hi> was by ſuch a Depoſition ſolemnly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign'd and tryed; and beſides, <hi>Sir Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Gaſcoign</hi> would perhaps have run the ſame riſque, had he not abſconded as ſoon as he got out of the <hi>Tower.</hi> I am ſure my being in <hi>Orders</hi> has no relation to the <hi>Plot,</hi> and puts not the leaſt grain into the Balance, ſince it will be no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of way plainer than before, ſhould I be deemed not only a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> but a <hi>Biſhop.</hi> Nor would I (certainly) be aſham'd of a Function (were I of it) of which, men as great in Quality, as emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in Learning, and as famous for San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:97478:62"/>as <hi>History</hi> can ſhow, have been. Nay from the ſame fountain, and no other, the <hi>Church of England</hi> her ſelf derives her <hi>Ordination.</hi> Let me then ſay thus much to <hi>Mr. Turbervile</hi> with my laſt <hi>Adieu;</hi> That ſhould God ever make me capable of this <hi>State of life,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline me to it (for 'tis no ill action, even in <hi>Law</hi> to be a <hi>Catholick Priest,</hi> and ſtop there) if the Ceremony ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd in the moſt open and publick man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that can be thought of, that ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity will be a perpetual <hi>Record</hi> againſt him, and conſequently an Evidence of the Injury he has done the Kingdom, to the manifeſting of his monſtrous folly and weakneſs in ſo groſs an accuſation.</p>
               <p>So much then for Mr. <hi>Turberville;</hi> and here I ſhould have ended were I not obliged to ſay ſomething, to what <hi>Sir William Jones</hi> thought fit to mention of me in my Lord <hi>Staffords Tryal.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">vid. p. 177.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">He doubts there of <hi>Mr. Lytcott</hi>'s being <hi>Fellow</hi> of <hi>Kings Colledge,</hi> becauſe ſuch places are beſtow'd (he hopes) on more deſerving and leſs ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious men, than he appears to be, that owns himſelf not only the <hi>Secretary,</hi> and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:97478:62"/>continual Companion of one <hi>ſo famous in the Popiſh Party as my Lord Caſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main</hi> is, but to have gone alſo and taken <hi>Notes</hi> at ſeveral <hi>Tryals,</hi> for his <hi>Lord's</hi> ſervice, who was concern'd in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt for <hi>Mr. Lytcott</hi>'s being <hi>Fellow</hi> of <hi>Kings Colledge,</hi> it will be acknowledg'd by the whole Body; and upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it was he became my <hi>Secretary;</hi> for having my ſelf had the ſatisfaction and honour to be a <hi>Fellow-Commoner</hi> of that <hi>Royal Foundation,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently acquainted with very worthy and excellent men, I knew not (till ſome better occaſion offer'd it ſelf) how to expreſs the great ſence I had of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and Civilities, but by having ever ſince my departure one of theirs ſtill with me. Mr. <hi>Lytcott</hi> had, 'tis true, ſome other accidental Recommendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as related to ſeveral perſons of very conſiderable faſhion and quality, whom I eſteem'd; Nor do I by any means deny the giving him order to take <hi>Notes</hi> at <hi>Tryals;</hi> nay this, or the equivalent, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd of others alſo, till I freed my ſelf from the calumny of the <hi>Plot.</hi> But had
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:97478:63"/>I known it a Crime againſt any Law ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther human or divine (and till I do, I cannot repent me of the Action) I ſhould not have ſent him, neither would he (I dare ſay) have gone; for his <hi>Colledge,</hi> and <hi>Friends</hi> cannot but own as well his great <hi>Probity,</hi> as his conſtant zeal for the <hi>Government.</hi> And as he (who very well knew it) atteſted, being ſummon'd to my <hi>Lord Staffords</hi> Tryal, <hi>that I was not at Powis Castle in the years</hi> 72 <hi>nor</hi> 73, ſo, by what I have here already ſhown, the whole matter has been prov'd and made good beyond the poſſibility of the leaſt doubt or ſcruple.</p>
               <p>In the next place, as to my being <hi>ſo famous in the Popiſh Party,</hi> as <hi>Sir William</hi> ſays I am, I do not know (I confeſs) what he means. Certainly that man is a very weak one, who (conſidering the hardſhips we ſtruggle with, the Obloquy we lie under, and the miſ-interpretation of all our actions) hopes to geat <hi>Fame</hi> by being a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> but if this <hi>Gentleman</hi> puts <hi>Fame</hi> in the worſt ſence, (for the word has oppoſite ſignifications) and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates, as if I were become to the World <hi>Infamous,</hi> by my <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:97478:63"/>I ſhall here in a few words give him a true and ſhort account of both.</p>
               <p>That I am a <hi>Catholick,</hi> I ſhall always acknowledge, as often as I am ask'd; but tho' my <hi>Religion</hi> were erronious, yet to me it muſt be a true and ſaving one, according to the <hi>Principles</hi> of our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt <hi>Adverſaries;</hi> for I have often, and diligently <hi>ſearcht the Scriptures,</hi> which they own to be the <hi>Rule of Faith;</hi> I have earneſtly <hi>pray'd to God</hi> (as they require) <hi>for his Illumination;</hi> I have <hi>argu'd with learned men,</hi> a thing too enjoyn'd by them; I have always been <hi>ready to give a Reaſon of my Belief, to whomſoever ſhould ask it of me,</hi> according to the <hi>Apostle</hi>'s advice, and theirs; and laſtly, I have <hi>read not only as much Controverſie,</hi> as, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, moſt men of my age in <hi>England,</hi> but <hi>twenty Proteſtant Books</hi> (I dare ſay) for <hi>one Catholick,</hi> and yet ſtill I am the ſame. Nor will any body (I hope) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend partiality or prepoſſeſſion in the caſe, ſeeing that muſt have much rather enclin'd me to the contrary ſide; for had I been of a <hi>Religion</hi> not obnoxious to the <hi>Laws,</hi> I might as well (it may be) have advanc'd my <hi>Fortunes</hi> as others, wanting
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:97478:64"/>(I thank God) neither <hi>Relations, Friends,</hi> nor <hi>Eſtate</hi> to give me a Riſe or begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Nay ſo great a propenſity have I ſtill for the <hi>Religion</hi> of all <hi>Governments,</hi> and particularly my own, that I thus far declare with Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> (who thought every body bound to be of his <hi>Prince</hi>'s Faith) <hi>that it is a great fault not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the eſtabliſh'd Practice in every particular, that is not truly ſinful in my Judgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis <hi>Conſcience</hi> then, that makes me a <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> and therefore I may be pitied, but not blam'd; for ſhould any <hi>Turk</hi> or <hi>Jew</hi> profeſs the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and yet in his heart think it falſe, he would be damn'd notwithſtanding the verity of it. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reaſon</hi> can demand nothing of one (as eminent <hi>Proteſtants</hi> tell us) but a <hi>ſincere Conviction;</hi> nor does the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeſt among them propoſe more. And if that ſhocking <hi>Article</hi> to fleſh and bloud, and reckon'd alſo by our <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> as our moſt dangerous <hi>Tenet,</hi> (I mean <hi>the real and ſubſtantial preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament)</hi> blots not a <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran</hi> out of the <hi>Book of Life,</hi> why ſhould it me? 'Tis true, we differ in the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:97478:64"/>
                  <hi>Mode</hi> or Manner of his being there, but not in the <hi>Reality;</hi> ſo that as great hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and as ſeeming contradictions ariſe to man's capacity from the one, as from the other opinion.</p>
               <p>To confirm further alſo, thoſe who might otherwiſe doubt of my being in the way of <hi>Salvation,</hi> as to <hi>Faith;</hi> I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly believe all thoſe very Points, <hi>which Proteſtant Divines call the grand Fundamentals of Chriſtianity;</hi> for I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the <hi>Incarnation;</hi> I believe the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> things as incomprehenſible and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to our finite Nature, as can be thought of; nor could any <hi>Doctrine</hi> be more ſtifly deny'd and rejected, than this has been by ſeveral <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> nay I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare as the <hi>Church of England</hi> does, when ſhe reads the <hi>Creed of St. Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> That <hi>whoſoever will be ſaved muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily hold what is there expreſs'd.</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve alſo in the <hi>Merits, Mediation,</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction of Chriſt,</hi> ſo that no <hi>Action</hi> of ours can poſſibly pleaſe but through his <hi>Merits;</hi> no <hi>Mediation</hi> of any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can have the leaſt force or weight, without the virtue of his <hi>Mediation;</hi> and no <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of ours can be valid,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:97478:65"/>but as it is grounded on, and perfected by the All-ſufficiency of his <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> I further believe, that <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Good Works</hi> muſt joyntly help in the great bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of <hi>Salvation;</hi> that both are <hi>God's gifts,</hi> and that we are not able ſo much as to think <hi>one good thought,</hi> or do the leaſt <hi>good Action,</hi> without his <hi>free Grace</hi> and Aſſiſtance. Laſtly, I believe that the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> are the <hi>Word of God;</hi> that the <hi>Reading of them</hi> is profitable; that it is lawful to have them in the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Tongue;</hi> but I believe (and the like perchance do all <hi>Chriſtian Churches)</hi> that there are <hi>ſome things</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>hard in them, which the unlearned and unſtable may wreſt to their own deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that they are not of a</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>private Interpretation.</hi> Now ſhould any judge otherwiſe, <hi>viz. That every body truly interprets, who ſincerely conſiders them,</hi> yet I am ſtill in the right; for then as a private man I think (and this with all ſincerity) that the <hi>hardneſs</hi> before expreſs'd, and the other words of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> (which intimate <hi>they are not of a private interpretation)</hi> ought to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in the plain and obvious ſence.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:97478:65"/>
               <p>If then by agreeing thus with <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> in what they call the <hi>chief Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of Chriſtianity;</hi> and if alſo by the conſent of their great and famous <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, ſeveral perſons</hi> (that have lived and died in our <hi>Religion) are in Heaven;</hi> for they ſtile them <hi>Saints,</hi> they admire their <hi>Actions,</hi> they propoſe them as <hi>Examples,</hi> and the like; I ſay, if then by reaſon of theſe things, I may rationally be aſſur'd that this <hi>Interior part</hi> of my <hi>Belief</hi> (to wit, that which principally relates to my ſelf) cannot <hi>damn me,</hi> I will now very ſtrictly examine the <hi>Exterior,</hi> or what touches others, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the matters that concern the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, As to <hi>Government</hi> in general, I believe <hi>Monarchy</hi> (from my heart) to be the beſt; and I think far the better of it, as often as I conſider our late Miſeries and Diſorders; yet had I been born in a lawful <hi>Commonwealth, Ariſtocracy,</hi> or <hi>Elective Kingdom,</hi> I ſhould look upon my ſelf bound in conſcience to defend the <hi>Eſtabliſhment,</hi> as I found it, (let it be which of theſe it will) againſt all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to the contrary, tho' they ſuited
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:97478:66"/>never ſo much with my own inclinations and Judgment.</p>
               <p>In the next place, I believe our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Soveraign <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d. to be the true, ſole and undoubted <hi>King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and that no <hi>Monarch</hi> in <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> has a more indiſputable <hi>Title</hi> to his <hi>Crown</hi> than He; which I look upon to be a great Bleſſing to his Subjects, being all oblig'd to obey, <hi>not only for wrath, but for conſcience ſake alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, I have been ſo far from hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (till Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> and others of the ſame ſtamp mention'd it) of any <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> or <hi>Declaration of Hereſie</hi> iſſu'd out againſt the <hi>King</hi> by his <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or any of that <hi>Church,</hi> that I am as much aſſur'd, that it is falſe, as that he never Chriſten'd or Confirm'd his ſaid <hi>Majeſty;</hi> for I have been twice my ſelf at <hi>Rome,</hi> and know that the <hi>Popes</hi> have ſtill ſpoken of him with great Honour and Reſpect: And beſides, there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet any <hi>Prence</hi> (always <hi>born</hi> and <hi>bred</hi> out of the <hi>Romiſh Communion</hi>) that underwent this <hi>Cenſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, were our <hi>King excommunicated</hi> and <hi>declared a Heretick,</hi> yet I do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:97478:66"/>believe, that it would be a horrible <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Sin</hi> in any <hi>Subject</hi> to <hi>Plot</hi> againſt, <hi>maim</hi> or <hi>hurt,</hi> and much more to <hi>kill</hi> him; and I do further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that every <hi>Engliſh, Scotch,</hi> or <hi>Iriſh</hi> man is in conſcience bound to prevent ſuch a miſchief, tho' it be with never ſo great a danger to his own life.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Doctrine of</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> further the <hi>Rep.</hi> to <hi>Anſwer</hi> of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. Apol.</hi> as alſo <hi>The Comp.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Kings,</hi> I never knew nor heard of any <hi>Religion,</hi> in which there were not ſome that have held it; nay not only <hi>Luther, Calvin, Zuinglius, Beza,</hi> and all the prime Leaders of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, have in expreſs terms declared the ſame, and practis'd it; but <hi>Pamphlets</hi> have been lately cry'd about the <hi>Streets,</hi> which boaſt, <hi>that there is no Reform'd Church from the</hi> Waldenſes <hi>to this day, that has not deem'd the procedure lawful.</hi> Now <hi>Papists</hi> are ſo far from holding it a <hi>piece of Faith,</hi> that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (the <hi>Pope</hi>'s great <hi>Champion</hi>) ſhows the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; and Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> (no ſmall Friend to his <hi>Holineſs</hi>'s power) calls it explicitely and plainly <hi>a Problematical Opinion.</hi> Nor has it only been written
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:97478:67"/>againſt, by ſeveral and ſeveral <hi>zealous Papists,</hi> but publickly and ſolemnly <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd</hi> in <hi>Popiſh Countries,</hi> in <hi>Popiſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> and by <hi>Popiſh Eccleſiaſticks</hi> themſelves.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> I am ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely for the binding part of it, as to my <hi>Duty,</hi> tho' there may appear ſome difficulty as to the wording of it; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that I ſhall moſt willingly take this very <hi>Oath,</hi> if (I ſay) a word or two were chang'd, or the ſtricteſt that ever was propos'd by <hi>Catholick Princes</hi> to their People; and truly I do ſincerely believe, that they are as careful of their ſafety and intereſt, and are as much <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of both, as any <hi>Governours</hi> upon the face of the whole Earth.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Oath</hi> of Supremacy, all <hi>Catholicks</hi> in the World agree in a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Dependency on <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo that even thoſe few that take this very <hi>Oath,</hi> do it, I ſuppoſe, upon a ſuppoſition or fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, (as they have it in their Books) That the <hi>Explanatory Act</hi> (in the 5th. of the <hi>Queen</hi>) declares, <hi>That ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to no Supremacy in ſpiritual matters;</hi> and thus the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Power is again (they
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:97478:67"/>think) reſtored, and the whole made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a bare <hi>Oath of Allegiance;</hi> but I make ſome doubt whether this was ever thought of by any <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and doubtleſs they are the beſt <hi>Interpreters</hi> of their own <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws.</hi> In ſhort, I deſign not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute any Point, but with all Modeſty and Candor to hint, why I cannot in Conſcience comply with theſe <hi>Oaths;</hi> neither do I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any way to leſſen the <hi>Regalia,</hi> or <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Power of our Kings;</hi> for I will ever defend it with my <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Fortune</hi> againſt all Perſons whatſoever; nor can <hi>Proteſtant Princes</hi> (I think) be enſlaved or ſubjuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our <hi>Opinion,</hi> ſince we find the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> ones to have been, and to be ſtill the freeſt and mightieſt <hi>Potentates,</hi> that we read of in the <hi>Chriſtian Commonwealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the Conſtitution and Frame of the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> I do admire it as the beſt that ever was, and beſeech <hi>God</hi> it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſo to the end of the World; nor does any thing more plainly demonſtrate to me, that the <hi>Principles of Popery</hi> tend not to a <hi>Tyrannick</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Sway,</hi> than that the <hi>Laws</hi> which preſerve our <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> were <hi>propos'd</hi> in the flouriſhing
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:97478:68"/>Times of that <hi>Religion</hi> by <hi>Popiſh Peers,</hi> were <hi>approved</hi> by <hi>Popiſh Commons,</hi> were <hi>put in execution</hi> by <hi>Popiſh Judges,</hi> and laſtly were <hi>deem'd</hi> ſo <hi>good</hi> and <hi>holy</hi> by the <hi>Popiſh Clergie,</hi> that they ſolemnly deſir'd <hi>God's Vengeance and Wrath</hi> to fall on the <hi>Infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> to <hi>Lye, Kill, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear,</hi> and the like, I do not only abhor them, and proteſt that I never heard from <hi>any Papiſt,</hi> that they are or were grantable; but I alſo declare, that I verily believe, That neither the <hi>Pope</hi> by himſelf, nor with a <hi>Council,</hi> can give me leave to commit ſuch <hi>Sin</hi> or <hi>Sins,</hi> or any <hi>Act</hi> now forbidden by <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>Law of Nature;</hi> and this I mean in the ordinary ſence, as every <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant</hi> underſtands it in the reading. Nor do I believe, that either the <hi>Church Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive,</hi> (and much leſs a ſingle man) can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a <hi>Sin, à parte ante,</hi> that is to ſay, before it be committed; and when it is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that it cannot be forgiven even by <hi>God</hi> himſelf, without hearty ſorrow in the <hi>Offender,</hi> and a reſolution never to do the like again; ſo that I look upon all <hi>Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers</hi> or <hi>Church-Papiſts,</hi> (as they are term'd) in a far worſe condition than an <hi>Infidel.</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:97478:68"/>This alſo I muſt beg leave to add here, that whereas many fancy and cry, that our <hi>Ghoſtly Fathers</hi> have a marvellous Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity among us, I do declare, that I verily believe, that there are no <hi>Prieſts</hi> among the <hi>Eaſtern Sects</hi> abroad, nor <hi>Miniſters</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> at home, nor in ſhort any <hi>Clergie</hi> among any <hi>ſeparate Chriſtians,</hi> but have forty times more intereſt in their reſpective <hi>Congregations,</hi> than the <hi>Popiſh</hi> have had here, theſe many and many years. That ſome particular man has had, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, power with his <hi>Patron,</hi> I do not deny, and the ſame I have known happen to a <hi>Valet de Chambre,</hi> to a <hi>Houſe-keeper,</hi> and it may be to <hi>Servants</hi> of an inferior degree; but ſo averſe generally are the <hi>Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks,</hi> I can ſay, (at leaſt ſince my time) to take the Directions of their <hi>Confeſſarius,</hi> in any thing that has a tendency to tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Affairs, that the beſt way oftentimes to perſwade ſome to a buſineſs, was to tell them, <hi>That the Prieſt did adviſe against it.</hi> What I here alledge, I am very confident is true; and for the further proof of it, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> of repute, that has ever been of our <hi>Communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Premiſſes then being the <hi>Credenda,</hi>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:97478:69"/>or ſum of my <hi>Religion</hi> and Belief in <hi>Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> there remains now a line or two of the <hi>Practice;</hi> and here alſo I ſhall ſhow my ſelf (to the diſſatisfaction of my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies) a zealous Lover of my <hi>Countrey;</hi> for truly I ever thought that this, and a ſincere devotion to the lawful eſtabliſh'd <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> were Synonimous words, and differ'd only in ſound.</p>
               <p>I had not (I confeſs) by reaſon of my years, an immediate ſhare in the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of the late Times, but I am ſure after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I felt great effects of them; for all my near <hi>Relations</hi> were not wanting, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their perſonal Attendance) in helping the then <hi>King</hi> with <hi>Men, Money, Plate,</hi> &amp;c. So that <hi>They</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwent for this Loyalty, <hi>Plunderings, Compoſitions, Decimations, Impriſonments,</hi> and the like, and <hi>Thoſe</hi> of the <hi>Catholick,</hi> the <hi>Confiſcation,</hi> and <hi>ſale</hi> of all they had. As for my ſelf, as ſoon as I came to <hi>Age</hi> and my <hi>Eſtate,</hi> I was no ways behind-hand in my actual Duty; for I ſent his preſent <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi> a very conſiderable <hi>Sum</hi> beyond Seas, and was ready alſo, <hi>Anno</hi> 59. (as not a few about him know) with <hi>Men, Horſes</hi> and <hi>Arms,</hi> to further his <hi>Reſtauration;</hi> for which
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:97478:69"/>(within a while after) I was impriſon'd, and had run the Fate of ſeveral of his other faithful Subjects, had not the Times alter'd as they did; then being choſen of the <hi>Free-Parliament,</hi> I had the ſatisfaction of voting his <hi>Return,</hi> and was ever as forward as any in expreſſing the Zeal and Service I had for him. Nor fail'd I alſo, (happening then to be in <hi>England</hi>) to hazard my life in the <hi>Dutch War;</hi> and when I return'd again into Foreign Parts, I did what I could (by the <hi>French Account</hi> I printed there) to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate the <hi>Lyes</hi> which tended to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Nation.</p>
               <p>'Tis not by way of Exprobration, that I offer this Memorial, but 'tis to remember the <hi>Reader,</hi> that a long ſeries of <hi>Loyal Actions,</hi> indicates a <hi>Loyal Heart,</hi> and that <hi>Habits</hi> are not loſt on a ſudden. I do alſo appeal to any man of Quality, I know in <hi>England,</hi> and to all I have been free with abroad, whether ever they heard me pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or defend <hi>Paradoxes</hi> in State-affairs, or found by any by-word a mutinous Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency; for I may ſafely aver, that there was never yet a <hi>Treaſon</hi> gradually carry'd on, where the <hi>Aſſociates</hi> (how wary ſoever they were in the main) have not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:97478:70"/>at ſome time or other, to raiſe <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents,</hi> to aggravate matters of <hi>Fact,</hi> and to alienate the minds of their Acquaintance from the <hi>Prince.</hi> But theſe were ſtill Actions ſo averſe to my nature, that I always ſteer'd a quite oppoſite courſe; nor did this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, I muſt ſay, (and I think every body is ſufficiently ſatisfy'd of it) in hopes of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment at <hi>Court,</hi> but it was in obedience and purſuance of thoſe juſt <hi>Principles,</hi> which the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> oblige a <hi>Subject</hi> to; and therefore I can call <hi>God</hi> to witneſs, that I never heard of any thing that tended to the temporal proſperity of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which did not elate and tranſport me; or if the contrary happen'd, that created me not an extraordinary trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and affliction.</p>
               <p>As for my private <hi>Tranſactions,</hi> I mean thoſe between man and man; whoſe <hi>Ox,</hi> whoſe <hi>Aſs</hi> have I taken; or to whom have I omitted the doing of a kindneſs, when I was oblig'd to it either out of Gratitude or Civility? I muſt confeſs, with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as to my <hi>Religion,</hi> I ever wiſht, and ſtill do, <hi>that all men were ſuch as I am except theſe Bonds;</hi> and I think every Perſwaſion does the like. I do alſo with him declare, <hi>That
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:97478:70"/>Evil cannot be done, that Good may come of it;</hi> ſo that I vow by all that is Holy, (ſince I hope that <hi>that Divine Grace,</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs, will alſo ſtrengthen) <hi>That I would not commit a premeditated ſin to convert the whole World;</hi> for God will be ſerv'd his own way, and when we do otherwiſe, 'tis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely far from a Service. <hi>Religion</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore never made me yet neglect a <hi>Friend,</hi> or poſtpone a <hi>Relation;</hi> and ſo conſtant I have ſtill been in this, that there are none of all my <hi>Proteſtant Kindred,</hi> but will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that my <hi>Affection</hi> has been as great, and my <hi>Zeal</hi> in their Concerns as intenſe, as if we had been of the ſame <hi>Faith.</hi> For my part, I always keep my <hi>Opinions</hi> to my ſelf, unleſs when I am ask'd the reaſon of them by ſome, or told Magiſterially by others, that nothing can poſſibly be ſaid to ſuch a Point: And if I chance to <hi>Write,</hi> it is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to my own <hi>Defence;</hi> nor can I think it a crime to <hi>Reply,</hi> when a man of Parts and Worth attacks me, for otherwiſe I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did, nor ever ſhall do it I am ſure. 'Tis not my profeſſion to make <hi>Converts;</hi> and truely when I accidentally met any, the uſual Encouragement from me was, what ſeveral of them experimentally have found
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:97478:71"/>and heard in <hi>Catholick Countries,</hi> where they now ſeek Relief, <hi>That Heaven was the only Gain to be expected by their Change;</hi> for <hi>Papiſts</hi> (I muſt ſay) are not ſo over-liberal as ſome think. <hi>Heaven</hi> (I thank God) was the only thing which I did, or could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to my ſelf; 'tis this alſo which aſſures me, if my <hi>Religion</hi> were true in mild wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it muſt needs be ſo in a Storm; and laſtly, 'tis this which made me always <hi>Loyal,</hi> and paſſionately to wiſh, That <hi>England</hi> might ſurpaſs both in <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Plenty,</hi> all the happy <hi>Nations</hi> that ſurround it.</p>
               <p>Thus having given <hi>Sir William</hi> an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my Principles both in <hi>Theory</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> (and if the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> obliges me to any one contrary <hi>Tenet,</hi> I abſolutely deny and reject it, which no body can do and be a <hi>Catholick.</hi>) I ſay, having given him this account, I hope for the future he will be ſo kind, as to believe I am greedy of no other <hi>Fame</hi> in the World, but to be deem'd (as I am) a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>faithful Engliſhman,</hi> and therefore when I make the leaſt ſtep or deviation out of the Road of Loyalty, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that this preſent Record under my own hand may riſe in Judgment to my eternal Reproach and Infamy.</p>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Amiens,</hi> 
                     <date>Mar. 7. 1681.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:97478:71"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:97478:72"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:97478:73"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:97478:74"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
